all right so we're going to talk about two or three topics today and the first
one is going to be kind of a review of some of the functions that exist inside
torch and kind of when and how to use them so the first the first set of
topics is about activation functions and there is a whole bunch of them defined
in in tight torch and they basically come from you know various papers that
people have written where they claim that this or that particular objective
function or activation function works better for their problem so of course
everybody knows the value that's very standard one but there's lots of
variations of values these values where the the the bottom part is not constant
and set to zero they can be allowed to change either only with the positive
slope or force to be to have a negative slope or sometimes being random in the
case of the randomized VQ value so they have you know a nice named likely key
value pair you revalue random value etc so the key value is one where you allow
the bottom part to have negative so and that kind of prevents the issue that
sometimes pops up that you know when radio is off it doesn't get any gradient
so here here you get a chance for that system that function to actually
propagate gradient and perhaps do something useful can go all the way to
kind of compete full ratification of the signal kind of like an absolute value
value it's well yeah the previous the previous activation was
is user using the discriminatory in again such that we always have gradients
going backwards for the generator and also these activation was necessary in
order to train the very skinny network I show at the beginning of the class
because again having like a very very skinny network it was basically
impossible to get gradients flowing back because we were like ending up in one of
the quadrants without you know where everything was zero out and then nothing
would have been actually trained if you wouldn't have
use you know this activation function that allows me to get some kind of
gradients even if we are in the regions where we are trying to suppress the
output so yeah right so a prelude is it's similar except now the the slope
and they get your side can be just about anything and okay what's what's
interesting about those all those functions that we just saw is that they
are scale invariant in the sense that they you know you can multiply the
signal by two and the output will not be changed
yeah I mean it would be multiplied by two but otherwise unchanged so they are
equivalent to scale there's no sort of intrinsic scale in those in those
functions right because there's only one non-linearity and it's a sharp one so
now we're getting into functions where the scale matters so the amplitude of
the incoming signal will affect the type of non the type of non-linearity that
you're going to get and one of those is the the soft press so soft rice it's
sort of a differentiable version of radio if you want it's it's kind of the
soft version of positive part and it's usually
permit rised as you can see at the top here
whatever Bay dialog 1 plus X financial beta X so it's it's kind of like the log
some exponential that we've been using a lot for service purpose except here one
of the terms in the sum is equal to 1 which is kind of like exponential zero
if you want so that looks like kind of a function that so synthetic ly is the
identity function for large policy values and asymptotically zero for
negative values so the approximate sir value it has a scale parameter though
this this beta parameter the larger beta the more the function will look like a
value so the cake will be kind of the corner will be kind of sharper if petah
goes to infinity but that that function has a scale
now you can prioritize those functions in in various ways and this is sort of a
another example of kind of a soft version of value if you
want where we're here you use value as a basis and then you add a small constant
to it that kind of makes it smooth you know I can't tell you that
any of those has any particular advantage over the others it really
depends on the only problem but they they all have kind of similar properties
if you want this also you can make sort of continuously closer to value that's
yet ok so when when difference here in this case is that this guy actually goes
negative right so unlike the value that has its minimum at zero this it's
horizontal asymptote at zero this guy goes below zero and that may or may or
may not be advantageous depending on the application you have sometimes it's
advantageous because it allows the system to basically make the average of
the output zero which is advantageous for certain types of for grading design
convergence the weights that are connected to units like this will see
both both positive and negative values which will then converge faster than if
you only see positive values so it's been the same here and it's just kind of
a differently you know a different permutation of kind of the same thing if
you want with different properties so of course there's tons of variations of
this you know with various parameters with different properties and you know
some of them that have particular properties that can relate them to
Gaussian distributions for example this is not the cumulative distribution of a
Gaussian but okay so those those were things that have one kinks in them and
if the kink is sharp there's no scale if the King has some scale in it there is
some scale but it's still sort of a single kick non-linearity now we're
getting into nonlinearities I have two kings okay so this one is basically a
saturating value I know sure white saturates at six you
know why not but why not parameterize this a little
better so here's a smooth function that you're familiar with because it's used
in in recurrent Nets in gated recurrent Nets and then STM
in soft max you know basically this is a a two-way soft max you can think of it
this way and this is just a function that goes kind of smoothly between 0 & 1
it's sometimes called a Fermi Dirac function as well because it derives from
some work in physics it's equal physics and then there is the hyperbola tangent
that we also talked about it's basically identical to the sigmoid except it's
centered so it goes between minus 1 and plus 1 and it's a little you know it's
twice the amplitude and the gain is a little different but it plays the same
role the advantage of hyperbolic tangent is
that the output is you can expect the output to not have zero mean but get
close to having zero mean and again that's advantageous for the weights that
follow because they see positive and negative values and they tend to
converge faster that's the case so I used to be a big fan of those
unfortunately if you stack a lot of sigmoids in many layers you know in a
neural net you you you can tend to not learn very efficiently you have to be
very careful about normalization if you want the system to to converge if you
have many layers so in that sense the the single kick functions are better for
deeper networks so it's signed this is basically a bit like the sigmoid except
that it's it doesn't get to the asymptotes as fast so it doesn't get
stuck towards the asymptotes as quickly so one problem with hyperbolic tangent
and and the sigmoid is that we get close to the asymptotes the the gradient goes
to zero fairly quickly and so if the weights of a unit become too large they
kind of saturate this unit and the gradients get very small and then the
the unit doesn't run very very quickly anymore it's a problem that
exists both sorry both in sigmoids and hyperbole tension and so such sign is a
function of that was proposed by your venue and so these collaborators and it
kind of saturates slower and so it doesn't have the that same problem I
mean it has the problem also but not to the same extent okay and this is kind of
the opposite heart tangent hard 10h I don't know if it deserves that name but
it's basically just a ramp okay and that works surprisingly well
particularly if your weights are somehow kept within a kind of small value so the
the units don't saturate too much it's surprising how well it works and you
know people use this and service context but that's sort of you know non-standard
so hard threshold is very rarely used because you can't really propagate
gradient to it okay and this is really what kept people from inventing back
prop in the 60s and 70s which is that they were using binary neurons and so
they didn't think of the whole idea of gradients because of that okay those
other functions are rarely used in the context of neural nets or at least for
kind of activation function in a traditional neuron that they used mostly
for sometimes for things like sparse coding so one step in sparse coding
consists in to compute the value of the latent variable consistent shrinking all
the values in the latent variable is the agent vector by some value and you do
this with a shrink function a shrinkage function this is kind of a soft version
of shrinkage function the hard version is here I mean it's called soft shrink
soft shrink but it actually has corners in it the reason it's called soft shrink
is because there is a hard shrink that looks different did that show you in a
minute so this basically just changes variable
by a constant toward zero right and if he goes below zero it connect its
client at zero if it if it's brought too long and so if the this is basically
just the identity function to which you subtract hyperbola tangent to make it
look like a shrink shrink basically design if we if we try to get the
whatever value close to zero and they actually are forced to zero basically
right right so small values are forced to zero others are shrunk toward zero
but you know it's a large enough they're not going to get to zero so again that's
used mostly as you know you can think of it as a step of gradient for an l1
criterion okay so if you have a variable you have
an l1 cost function on it and you take a step in the negative gradient of the one
so every one cost is an absolute value this will cause the variable to kind of
go towards zero by a constant which is the slope of that at one criterion and
to kind of stay at zero you know coming from either side it doesn't kind of
overshoot if you want and so that that's an on-ear function you use and that's
one of the steps in the East algorithm that is used for inference in in sparse
coding but again it's it's really used in sort of regular neural nets unless
your encoder is kind of used as kind of a estimation of sparse coding this is
the hard shrink so hard shrink basically clients every value smaller than lambda
to zero okay so if a value is smaller than lambda or larger than - from there
sort of between minus lambda lambda when lambda is some constant is just set it
to zero again it's used for things like you know certain types of sparse coding
but rarely as an activation function in the night so log sigmoid is mostly used
in cost functions not really as an activation function either but it's a
useful function to have if you want to plug this into into a loss function and
we'll see we'll see that ten minute so something we've seen this is the same
as softmax except you have minus signs so this is sort of more so that so those
are multi-dimensional nonlinearities all right you you have a vector in and you
get a vector out which is at same size as the input vector and we know about
softmax is you know exponential X I divided by sum over J exponential X J
this is such min where you put a minus sign in front of the X so you view the
X's if you want as energies instead of scores as penalties instead of scores
it's a good way of turning a bunch of numbers to something that looks a bit
like a probability distribution which means numbers between 0 and 1 that's 1
to 1 and that's the softmax which we all know so locks off max again it's not
very much used as a non-linearity within the neural net but it's used a lot at
the output as kind of one piece of a loss function it will see this in a
minute ok so those questions yes we have a question so for pre low I'm not sure I
understand number one why we want the same value for all channels and number
two how learning a it would actually be advantages you could have a different a
for different channels so different units can have a different a it could be
you could use it this as a as a parameter very every unit or not you
could be shared that's gonna up to you it could be shared at the level or a
feature map it accomplished on that or it could be share all future maps or it
could be individual to every unit if you really want to preserve the coalitional
nature of a commercial net you probably want to have the same a for every unit
in the future that but you think you can have different aids for different
feature Maps okay well it's the second question why learning actually a
specific value would be advantages like why are we learning a you can learn it
or not you can fix it the the reason for fixing it would be you know not
necessarily to kind of have sort of more powerful non-linearity but to kind of
ensure that the non-linearity gives you a non 0 gradient even if it's even if
it's in the negative region so you know runnable not nor lib not renewable so to
make it learnable allows the system to basically turn a non-linearity into
either the linear mapping which of course is not particularly interesting
but why not value or something like a full rectification okay where a would be
minus 1 in the in the negative part which you know can be it can be
interesting for certain types of application so for example if you have
accomplish on that that has an edge detector an edge detector as a priority
right it's it's got press coefficients on one side minus coefficients on the
other side and so it's gonna react so if you have an edge in an image that goes
from say dr. bright the you know the composition will react positively to
this one but if you have another edge from from you know in the opposite
direction then the the react the the filter will react negatively now if you
want your filter to react to an edge regardless of its priority you rectify
it okay so that would be kind of just absolute value now you could of course
bake this in you know how to use a prelude you can just use the absolute
value probably a better idea is to use a square actually so you take the square
of square non-linearity it's not implemented as kind of a neural net
non-linearity but you know in the functional form of by torture just right
square and that's it hope answered the question
any other question on this topic I have a question it seems to me like these
nonlinearities are trying to basically make a linear function nonlinear and the
tweak in the in the lines denote like the change in that function so they can
we think of this as if we want to model of curve in the line should we have
learnable on both like before before the 0 and
after the 0 on the x-axis like well so yeah I mean there is diminishing return
so the question is you know how complex do you want your non-linearity to be so
you could imagine of course primate rising an entire nonlinear function you
know with sprite parameters or busy curves or something like this right or I
don't know chebyshev polynomials you know I mean you can probably try any any
mapping you want right you can imagine those those parameters could be part of
the learning process however you know what is the advantage of doing this
versus just you know having more units in your in your system and relying on
the fact that multiple units will be added in the end to approximate the
function you want generally it really depends on what like if you want to to
do regression in a fairly low dimensional space so perhaps you want
some parameterize nonlinearities that might help you might have like you might
want to have a collection of different nonlinearities with maybe things like
like gbj polynomials if you want to do good approximation approximations but
for like you know high dimensional tasks like image recognition or things like
this you just want a non-linearity and it works better if the non-linearity is
monotonic otherwise it creates all kinds of issues because you could have two
points that will produce the same output and so it's you land videos for the
system to learn the right function there so you want it it's it's much better if
the function is monotonic and almost all the functions here are monotonic except
if you have a negative a here in the in the prelude case there's big advantage
to having monotonic functions but in principle you could probably try as you
know any function you want people are played with this you know they're not
very popular because mostly they don't seem to be bringing a huge advantage in
in the kind of applications that people use a large neural nets for other
questions another question is going to be keen commercial smooth yeah
I should never have any application with the choice so funny
yeah teas made of bacon packed the only thing I'm aware of is using a single
function silica double King for DPL networks healthily in better well so
here's a party with double kick double kick has a built-in scale in it which
means if you're it's a waste of the incoming layer are multiplied by two or
the signal amplitude is multiplied by 2 the result on the output would be
completely different right yeah because you will be you know the signal would be
more in the non-linearity so so you'll get completely different behavior of
your layer whereas if you have a function with only one King if you
multiply the input by two with the output it's also multiplied by two in a
modulo bias but the signal device is fine so what I mean to ask you something
of a situation with a choice of activation function made a big
difference in the performance of the model except for the in networks using
today move instead of sigmoid there is no sort of general answer to this like
if you're going to use attention you have to use softmax I mean you have no
choice right I mean it's not like you have to use shaft softmax but you want
to have something where you get coefficients right to to kind of focus
the attention of the system on or to kind of spread the attention of the
system and not allow it to cheat which is to pay attention to multiple things
at one time you have to have some sort of normalization of the of the
coefficients that come out of the attention system right so so normally in
most attention systems like in transformers and stuff the the
coefficients are passed through softmax so you get a bunch of coefficients that
are between 0 & 1 & 7 to 1 and so that causes the system to have to pay
attention to you know a small number of things right you can only concentrate
the coefficients on a small number of items and it has to spread it right
there are other ways to do normalization you you can do and in fact is something
that's wrong with softmax normalization for for for transformers or for
attention which is that if you want a coefficient coming out with softmax to
be close to zero you need the input to be close to minus
infinity okay or to be considerably smaller than the largest one right when
you go into the softmax when I put the largest input is going to cause the
corresponding output to be the to be large if you want that I'd put to be
close to one and all the other ones to be close to zero you basically want this
input to be extremely large and all the other ones to be large and negative okay
now that you know that that can be a problem when the what you are computing
the input are our dot products because the result is that you know the easiest
way for a system to to produce a small dot product is to have two vectors that
are orthogonal to each other which gives the dot product is zero if you insist
that the dot product should be very very small
then either you have to make the so you have to make the two vectors basically
point in opposite directions and you have to make them very long and that's
not so great and so using softmax for attention basically limits the the the
contrast that you're gonna have between two coefficients which is not
necessarily a good thing so you know same thing for ASTM gates
gated recurrent Nets etc you you need Sigma it's there because you need
coefficients there are between 0 and 1 you know that either
we set the memory cell or make it a fast-food so that it keeps it so it's
previous memory or kind of right the the new input in it so there it's nice to
have an output that varies continuously
between zero and one there you have no choice so I mean I don't think you can
say just you know in generic term you know this this non-linearity is better
than this other one there are certain cases where it learns better though
certain cases where it relieves you from having to initialize properly the
certain cases where it works better if you have lots of layers like you know
single click functions work better if you have lots of layers better than
Sigma large functions there's no kind of logical answer I had a question just
regarding the general differences between a nonlinear activation that has
kinks versus a smooth nonlinear activation yeah is there sort of any
general reason or rule to why we would prefer to have kinks in the function or
not it's a matter of scale invariant of scale equivariance so if the kick is
hard again you multiply the input by 2 the output is multiplied by 2 but
otherwise unchanged okay if you have a smooth transition if you multiply the
input by let's say 100 the output now will look like you had a hard kick okay
because the the smooth part now it's become shrunk by a factor of 100 if you
divide the input by 100 now the the cake becomes a very very smooth sort of
convex functions okay so it changes the behavior but by changing the scale the
input you change the behavior of the of the unit and that might be a problem
sometimes because when you when you train a multi-layer neural net and you
have two layers that are one after the other you don't have a good control for
like how big the weights of this layer are relative to that other way so
imagine you have a two layer Network where you don't have a non-linearity in
the middle so the system is completely linear right if the network has arrived
at the solution you can multiply the incoming the the first layer weight
matrix by two divide the second weight matrix by two
and overall the network will have exactly the same output okay you won't
have changed anything and what that means is that when you do training there
is nothing that forces the system to have a particular scale for the weight
matrices all right so now if you put a non-linearity in the
middle and you still don't have it because train for the system to kind of
you know have scales for the first leg of weight versus the second leg away
that you know you'd better have a non-linearity that doesn't care about
scale okay so if you have non-linearity that does care about scales about scale
then your network doesn't have a choice of what size weight matrix it can use in
the first layer because that will completely change the behavior and you
may want to have large weights for some other reason which will saturate the
non-linearity and then kind of create you know vanishing gradient issues so I
it's not entirely clear you know what why is it that you know did networks
work better with single King functions but it's probably due to that scale
invariance property let's get a quick variance property now there would be
other ways of fixing this fixing this problem which would be to basically set
a heart scale on the weights of every layer so you couldn't like normalize the
weights of the layers so that the the the variance that of things that go into
unit you know it's always constant in fact that's a little bit with batch
normalization does so the various normalization schemes they do that to
some extent you know they could mean at zero and and the variance is constant so
so now the variance of the amplitude of the output doesn't depend on the size of
the weights because it's not wise so you know that is partially why things like
like like that norm and good norm and things like this help is because they
can fix the scale a little bit but then if you fix the scale then with something
like that norm you don't the system now doesn't have any way of choosing which
part of the non-linearity it's going to use in the to cake function system
okay so things like group normalization or batch normalization are incompatible
with kin sigmoids if you want share a sigmoid you don't want normalization
just before it see that provides some really good intuition thank you okay I
have one more question I noticed in a soft malfunction some people use the
temperature coefficient so in what cases would we want to use their temperature
and why would we use it well to so to some extent the temperature is redundant
with incoming weights so if you have weighted sounds coming into your softmax
you know having a data parameter in your softmax equal to two instead of one it's
the same as just making your waste twice as big it has exactly the same effect
okay so that beta parameter is redundant with the size of the weights but again
if you were or the size of the weighted sum the variance of the weighted stones
if you want but again if you have a batch normalization in there then the
temperature parameter matters because now the input variances are fixed so so
now the the temperature matters temperature basically new controls how
hard the the you know the the distribution on the output will be so
with a very very large beta you basically will have one of the outputs
equal to one and all the other ones really close to zero I mean very close
to one and very close to zero where beta is small then this software in the limit
of beta equal to zero it's more like an average actually that you get like soft
max behaves a little bit like an average so you know beta goes infinity at it so
behaves a bit like AG Max and there goes to zero it behaves of it like reckon
average so so if you have some sort of normalization before the softmax then
tuning is parameter allows you to control this could have hardness and
what people do sometimes in certain scenarios is that they start with a
relatively low beta so that the the numbers that are produced are kind of
soft so you get gradients everywhere you know it's kind of well-behaved in terms
of gradient and then as running proceeds if you want
kind of harder decisions in your attention mechanism or whatever you
increase data and so that makes the system kind of make harder decisions it
doesn't run as well anymore but it's you know presumably after a few iterations
it's kind of in the right ballpark so you can sort of sharpen the the
decisions there but can be increasing data it's useful for example in a
mixture of mixture of experts and you know self attention systems are kind of
you can think of as sort of a form of a weird form of mixture of experts so a
mixture of experts you know you have multiple sub networks and their outputs
are can linearly combine with coefficients that are the output of the
softmax itself could you know controlled by another neural net so if you want
kind of a soft mixture you have a low beta and as you increase their to
infinity basically you're going to select one of the experts and ignore all
the other ones there might be useful for example if you want to train a mixture
of experts or an attention mechanism but in the end you want to save computation
by just determining which expert do I need to compute and just not computing
the other ones so in that case you want those coefficients to be basically
either one or zero and and you can train the system progressively to do this by
increasing increasing data this is called the physicists have a name for
this because it uses kind of tricks or various other things that's called
annealing it has the same meaning as so annealing comes from metalwork right you
you're making a steel or something and you make a sword or something right and
you heat it up and then you you you you you cool it and depending on whether you
cool it quickly or slowly you'll you change the crystal no crystalline
structure of the of the metal so this idea of annealing of progressively
lowering the temperature correspond to this increasing this beta beta is like
an inverse temperature it's akin to an inverse temperature any other question
I think we are good all right okay so next topic is lost functions so PI torch
has a whole bunch of loss functions as you might have seen and of course there
are things are simple ones like like mean square error so I don't need to
explain to you what it is you know compute the square of the error between
the desired output Y and actually I put X and if it's already bet with n samples
then you have you know n losses one for each of the samples in the batch and you
can you can tell this last function to either keep that vector or to kind of
reduce it by academia or some okay pretty simple mmm here's a different
loss that's the everyone knows so this is basically the absolute value of the
difference between between the desired output and the actual output and you
want to use this to do what's called robust regression so if you want small
errors to count a lot and large errors to count but you know not as much as if
you use the square perhaps because you have noise in your
data so you know that you have a bunch of data points you're trying to kind of
train and know on that to something to kind of you know fit a curve or you know
do regression but you know that you have a few outliers so you have a few points
there are you know very far away from what they should be just because you
know the system as noise or something or the data was collected with with some
noise so you want the system to be robust to that noise you don't want the
cost function to increase too quickly as the points are far away from you know
the kind of the general curve so at one loss will be more robust now the problem
with that one loss is that it's not differentiable at the bottom and so you
know you have to kind of be careful when you get to the bottom of how you how you
do the the gradient that's basically done with this soft shrink essentially
that's that's the everyone knows now to correct for that
people have come up with various ways of kind of making the l1 notes for bus for
large losses but then still smooth at the bottom kind of behaving like squad
error at the bottom so an example of this is is this particular function
smooth say one loss it's basically a one far away and it's sort of l2 nearby and
that presents sometimes that's called a Google loss some people call this also
elastic Network because it's an old paper from the 1980s or 1990s that kind
of proposed this this kind of objective function for different purpose so that's
useful that was advertised by was gaerste confess our CNN paper for and
it's used quite a bit in Cuba division for survivors purposes again it's for
protecting against outliers sharper jesus also sharper results now when we
do like image prediction sharper than using the MSE not particularly I mean
it's it's just like the MSE for small errors okay so that doesn't make any
difference but it it doesn't or maybe I misunderstood what your point
was sorry I was trying to compare the l1 versus the in the l2 that the l2 gives
us like usually blurry blurry predictions whenever we try to do
prediction by using like the l2 minimizing the l2 weather whereas like
people are minimizing the l1 in order to have like sharper overall predictions
okay so if you take if you take a bunch of points okay if you take a bunch of
y-values okay and you ask the question what value so you take a bunch of points
on on why okay yeah you ask the question what value of y minimizes
the squirrel Ellis the answer is that it's the average of all the whites okay
okay so if you so if for a single X you have a whole bunch of wise which means
you have noise in your data your system will want to produce the average of all
the ways that you're observing okay and if the Y you're observing is not a
single value but is I don't know an image the average of a bunch of images
is a blurry image okay that's why you get those very effects
now with air one the value of y that minimizes the l1 norm the l1 distance so
basically the sum of the absolute values of the differences between the value
you're considering and all the points all the white points that's the median
okay so it's it's a given point all right uh-huh and I see media and of
course it's not blurry it's just an image although it's kind of difficult to
define in multiple dimensions but so one problem with this loss is that it has a
scale right so here the transition here is at point five but why should it be at
point five you know it could be it depends what the scale of your of your
errors are okay negative exactly who lost this is really not the negative of
likelihood loss I'm not sure why it's called this way by torch but basically
here imagine that you have an X vector coming out okay and you your loss
function is there is one correct X okay so imagine each X correspond to a score
for lies a multi-class classification right so you have a desired class which
is one particular index in that vector okay now what you want is you want to
make that score as large as possible okay if those scores are likelihoods
then this is minimum negative log likelihood if those scores are log
likelihoods and this is maximum likelihood or minimum negative log
likelihood okay but there is nothing in this module
that actually specifies that the elds have to be log likelihoods so this is
just you know make my desired component as large as possible that's it
if you put negative signs in front so now you you can interpret the axis as
energies as opposed to scores okay they're not called six-course they're
like they're like penalties if you want but it's the same so the formula here
says you know just pick the X that happens to be the correct one for one
sample in the batch and make that score as large as possible now this particular
one allows you to give a different way to different to different categories
which is W those w's it's a it's a weight vector that gives a way to each
of the each of the categories it's useful in a lot of cases particularly if
you have widely different frequencies for the for the categories you might
want to increase the weight of samples for which you have a small number of
examples I mean for categories for which you have a small number of samples
however I'm actually not a big fan of this of this I think it's a much better
idea to just increase the frequency of the of the samples from the classes for
the class I have you know that appears rarely so that you equalize the
frequency the frequencies of the classes when you train it's much better because
it exploits stochastic gradient in a better way okay so so the bottom line of
that is if you have let me actually draw a picture of this so let's say you have
a problem where you have tons of samples for category one and then the small
number of samples for category two in a tiny number of samples for category
three you could so let's say you know here you have I don't know a thousand
samples and here you have 500 samples and you have I don't know
200 samples right so you could do is using this this kind of weight function
you could give this a weight of of 1 and this guy weight of 2 and this guy weight
of 5 and then you can equalize the weights if you want it's really better
to make sure that the way it's normalized to 1 that would be probably a
better idea but what I recommend is not that what I recommend is when you pick
your samples you basically pick one sample from class 1 and then one sample
from class 2 and super from class 3 and then you know you keep doing this during
your training session and when you get to the end of class 3 you go back to the
beginning ok so you keep going here but here you go back to the first sample
keep going here go back and now you have the second sample ok and now you get to
the end of class to go back to the start ok so the next sample is going to be
here here and here and then the next one here here and here here here and then
this guy wraps around again etc right so you basically have equal probability
equal frequencies for all the categories but just going through those kind of
circular buffers more often for categories for which you have fewer
samples ok once you should absolutely never do is equalize the frequencies by
by just not using all the samples in categories that are frequent I mean
that's horrible you should never let any data on the floor it's never any reason
to leave that on the floor ok now here's a problem with this the problem with
this is that after you've trained your your neuron that to do this you know one
that does not know about the relative likelihood the relative frequencies of
the samples and so let's say this is a system that those medical diagnoses it
doesn't know that the common cold is a way more frequent than you know lung
cancer or something right so what you need to do in the end is do a pass a few
passes perhaps where you can fine tune your system so that with the actual
frequencies of the categories and the effect of this is going to be for the
system to adapt the biases at the output layer so that the likelihood of you know
diagnosis corresponds to the the frequency of it right it's gonna favor
things that are more frequent the reason why I don't want to do this during the
entire training is because if you train a multi-layer net the the the system
basically never develops the right features for rare cases and they have
spoken about this already in the class in in past weeks to kind of recycle the
example of medical school you you don't spend when you go to medical school you
don't spend time studying the food that is proportional to the frequency of the
food with respect to very rare diseases for example right you spend basically
the same time studying all the diseases in fact you spend more time studying
complicated one which usually tend to be rarer and that's because you need to
develop the features for it okay and then you need to kind of correct for the
fact that you know those rare diseases are rare so you don't do that that you
know you don't suspect the diagnosis for rare diseases very often because you
know it's rare okay so that's all for for weights question tributo so you'll
be using this a lot of course and cross country pillows is a kind of merging of
two things merging of lot softmax function and negative low likelihood
loss okay and so and the reason why you want to have this is for numerical
reasons so the locks off max is you know
basically the softmax followed by log right so you first compute the softmax
then you do the log if you do softmax and then log and you back propagate
through this you might have gradients in the middle between the log and the
softmax that end up being infinite so for example if if the the maximum value
of one of the stars max is close to one and some of the other ones are close to
zero you take the log you get something that's close to minus infinity you back
propagate through the log you get something that's close to infinity okay
because the the slope of vlog goes to zero is very very close to infinity but
now you multiply this by a soft max that is saturated so it's multiplied by
something that's very close to zero so in the end you get a reasonable number
but because the intermediate numbers are close to infinity or 0 you multiply plus
something that's close to plus infinity by something that's close to 0 you get
numerical issues so you don't want to separate log and soft max you want to do
lots of Max in one in one go it simplifies the formula it makes the
whole thing much more stable numerically and for similar reasons you also want to
merge lots of Max and get you really good loss so basically if you have locks
off Max and you get you've log-likelihood loss it says I got a
bunch of weighted sums and a percent through soft max I'm going to take the
log of those and then I want to make the the output of the log short max for the
correct class as large as possible okay that's what the negative load actually
lost does it wants to make the score of the correct class as large as possible
we saw that just a minute ago right when you back propagate through the blocks
off max as a consequence it's going to make the score of all the other classes
as small as possible right because of the normalization and
so that you know that's why sometimes the the whole idea of sort of building a
network by you know modules sometimes there is an advantage instead
of merging in modules into single wine by end right so so the cross
entropy does in fact this explains a little bit you know those numerical
simplifications so the loss you know takes an X Factor and a category a
desired category a class okay and computes the negative log of the softmax
applied to the vector of scores but the one that's on the numerator numerator
here is the the X of the index of the correct class okay so that's that's your
loss the negative log of exponential the score of the correct class divided by
the sum of the Exponential's all the scores okay you can think of the X's as
negative energies okay it's completely equivalent now when you do the math and
you simplify your the log and the Exponential's gonna simplify and so you
just get the score of the correct class the negative score of the correct class
okay so to make that small you make the score large and then press the log of
the sum of the Exponential's of the scores of all the other class to make
that small you make all the edges small negative as far as fat you know as
negative as possible okay so this will make the score of the correct class
large like this core of everything else small again like in the aisle you can
you can have a weight per category also there is a physical interpretation right
of the cross entropy right okay so why is it called course entropy because it
is the cross entropy between two distributions
it's the KL divergence really between two distributions
it doesn't appear clearly here in this formula but think of the softmax applied
to the X vector as a distribution okay so take the X Factor's this course
rather than to a softmax you get a bunch of numbers between 0 & 1 that's 1 2
and now you have a desired distribution and the desired distribution the target
distribution if you want is one in which all the wrong categories had zero and
the correct category has one okay now compute the KL divergence between those
two distributions okay so it's the sum over indices of the correct probability
okay which is zero for except for one term times the ratio between the log of
the the probability that the system produces and the correct probability
which is one okay so all of those terms you know reduce to kind of a single term
which is just the one for which the correct probability term is one okay so
we end up with this with this term it's just a negative log of the softmax
output for the correct class okay we can use this as a cross entropy between the
distribution produced by the system and the one hot vector corresponding to the
desired distribution if you want okay so now there is a there would be another
can a more sophisticated version of this which would be the actual KL divergence
between the distribution produced by the system and a distribution that you
propose whatever it is a target distribution which now is not binary
it's not the one hard vector anymore but it's just a vector of numbers and that's
called the KL divergence in fact it's we'll see it in a minute so Kerala
vergence is a kind of you know it's not a distance because it's not symmetric
but it's a sort of a divergence between between distributions discrete
distributions okay so this one is a bit of a kind of a extension if you want of
lakhs of Max and it's a version of it that is applicable for very very large
categorization so if you have many many many categories what you might want to
do is kind of cut some corners you don't want to compute the giant softmax over
million categories or maybe even more so there you can sort of basically ignore
the ones that are small and you know kind of use tricks to kind of you know
improve the speed of the of the computation and this is what this does
I'm not going to go into the details exactly what it does because actually I
don't know the details but but it's basically an efficient approximation
softmax for a very very large number of categories so this is a special case of
course entropy when you only have two categories and in that case it kind of
reduces to something simple so this does not include stuff max this is just a
quest entropy when you have two categories and as I as I said before the
the the cross entropy loss is the sum of our categories of the probability I mean
some of our indices or some of our categories of the probability for the
target the target probability for that category times the ratio between the log
of the probability for of produced by the system divided by the probability of
the target category and if you work it out for two categories necessarily one
score is one minus the other one if you have two exclusive categories and and it
comes down to this okay now this presupposes that x and y
is x and y are kind of probabilities they have to be between strictly between
0 & 1 I mean not strictly but well kind of
strictly because otherwise the logs gonna blow up here is the KL divergence
process I was to tell you about earlier so here it's the
I mean it it's it's real turn here in a funny form but it's basically the here
again it's it sort of assumes this is another one I was telling you about
earlier actually this one is also a simplified one when you have a a one hot
distribution for the target so why is it's a category but it has the
disadvantage of not being merged with something like softmax or log softmax so
it may reach I mean it may have kind of numerical issues again it assumes x and
y are you know distributions this is values personal loss okay so
this version of binary choice entropy here takes scores that haven't gone
through sigmoid so this one does not assume that X the x's are between 0 & 1
it just takes you know values whatever they are and it it passes them to a
sigmoid to make sure there are between 0 & 1 strictly ok and so that is more
likely to be a numerically stable it's a bit the same ideas kind of emerging
locks off max and you get your lucky hood very yeah same thing here that's
what I was talking okay margin losses so this is sort of a important category of
losses those losses basically say if I have in this case two inputs the last
function here says I want one input to be larger than the other one by at least
two margin okay so imagine the two inputs or scores for two categories you
want the score for the correct category to be larger than the score for the
incorrect category but it hits some margin that you passed through the
system and that's the the formula you see down there so it's basically a him
okay and it takes the difference between the two scores and so why is a binary
variable this plus one or minus one and it controls whether you want X to be
larger than x1 to be larger than x2 or whether you want x2 to be larger than x1
okay we basically give you two scores and you tell it which one you want to be
the larger score and then the cost function says you know if this one is
larger than that one by at least a margin then the cost is zero if it's if
if it's smaller than the margin or if it's in the other direction and the cost
increases linearly okay so that's called a hingeless okay so that's very useful
for a number of different things we've we've seen an example of this in so yeah
for example so this is sort of a margin ranking class so you have two values but
there are sort of is a simplified version of it I mean there's a simpler
version of it which I don't have here for some reason we only have an X okay
so basically the loss is max of 0 and minus X times the margin and it just
wants to make to make X smaller than the margin right and so this is sort of a
special case where you have a ranking between two scores of two categories so
here is how you would use this for classification you would basically run
your classifier you would get scores ok idea so before you do any non-linearity
weighted sums and then you know the correct category so you say I want this
correct category to have a high score and then what you do is you take another
category that has the most offending score so either another category so a
category that is incorrect that has a higher score than the correct one or
that has a lower score but the lowest score is too close ok so you take the
the category that whose core is the closest to the to the correct one or who
score is higher than the correct one and you feed those two scores to the last
function like this so basically it's going to push up the score in the
correct category push down the score the incorrect category until the difference
is that eastern margin equal to the margin okay that's you know a perfectly
good way of training something in the context of an energy-based model for
example that's the sort of things you might want to do you might want to say X
1/4 minus x1 is the energy I mean X you know minus X 1 will be the energy of the
correct answer and minus X 2 would be the energy of the incorrect answer like
an a contrastive term an incorrect answer and you want to push down the
energy of the correct answer which are the energy of incorrect answer so that
the difference is at least some margin okay can use this kind of laws for that
the to play Clause is gonna be refinement on this so this is used a lot
for metric learning for the kind of Sammys nets that each n was each and
mister I was talking about last week and and there the idea is let's say I have a
distance so let's say I have three samples I have one sample and another
sample is very similar to it I've run them through to commercial Nets I get
two vectors I compute the distance between those two vectors D of a IP I
for example okay I want to make this distance as small as possible because
that's the core example and then I take two samples that I know are semantically
different ok the image of a cat and whatever table and I want to make the
vector as far away from each other so I compute the distance I want to make this
distance large alright now I can insist that the first is done B zero and it can
insist that the second distance be larger than the margin that would be
kind of a margin loss type type thing but what I can do is one of those
triplet margin notes where I say the only thing I care about is that the
distance that I get for the good is smaller than the distance that I get
for the bad pit I don't care if the distance is small I just wanted to be
smaller than the distance for the bad pair okay and that's what those ranking
goes to a bunch of those were I mean one of the first I think that was proposed
was by Chisholm Weston and Sammy bengio back when Jaden Weston was today Google
and they used this to train kind of an image search system for Google so back
then I'm not sure is true anymore but back then you would type a query on
Google Google would encode that query into a vector then we compare this to a
whole bunch of vectors describing images that I've been previously indexed and
and then would kind of retrieve the images whose vector were close to the
one that that you had and the way you train those those the networks that
compute those vectors in that case back then it was in your networks actually as
you train them with those trip pillows okay so you said good hits for my search
should should have a distance between the vectors that is smaller than any bad
hit and I don't care if the distance is small I just wanted to be smaller than
for that it's any question that's kind of a graphical explanation of this where
P is a positive sample so it's you know similar to a so a is the sample you
considered P is kind of a positive sample and N is a negative sample
contrast example you want to push anyway and bring P closer and as soon as P is
closer than n by some margin you you stop pushing and pulling your soft
versions of this and in fact you can think of nce the the kind of loss
function that hn was talking about as kind of a soft version of that where you
basically you have a bunch of positives and bunch of negatives or you have one
positive and bunch of negatives and you run them through softmax and you say
I want this the you know e to the minus distance for the correct one to be
smaller than you know e to the minus the other one so it kind of you pushes the
positive closer to you and pushes the other ones further to you but now with
some sort of stuff maxi that sort of exponential decay as opposed to sort of
a hard margin so in PI torch you have things that allow you to have multi
labels so this allows you to basically give multiple correct outputs so instead
of you know this is a ranking Mouse but it's serving sitting that there is only
one correct category and you know you you you want a high score for the
correct category and that's core for everything else here you can have a
number of categories for which you want high scores and then all the other ones
will get pushed away all right we'll get the scores will be
pushed down so here it's a it's a hinge loss but you do a sum of those this
hinge loss overall categories and and for each category if the category is a
desired one you push it up if it's a non desire one you push it down which is
what this video formula says and of course you have the soft version of this
which I'm not going to go into the details of and the multi margin version
of it so this pushing and pulling for metric learning for embedding for Sammis
nets that I would say telling you about it's actually kind of all implemented if
you want in one of those engine vending laws so engine 30 loss is a loss for
Siamese nets that kind of pushes things are semantically similar to you and push
away things that are not okay so the Y variable indicates whether the pair you
are or whether the score you are giving to the system is one that should be
pushed up a window should be pushed down and it it chooses the hinge loss that
makes the score positive if Y is plus one and it makes a
score negative by some margin Delta if if Y is minus one
very often when you are doing Siamese Nets the way you compute the
similarity between two vectors is not through Euclidean distance between
cosine distance so the one minus the cosine between the of the angle between
the two vectors this is basically a normalized Euclidean distance if you
want you can think of it this way the advantage of this is that whenever you
can push the distance whenever your two vectors and you want to make the
distance as large as possible there's a very easy way for the system to get away
with it by making the the two vectors very large very long you know not
pointing in the same direction and make them very very long so now the distance
would be large but of course that's not what you want you don't want the system
to just make the the vectors bigger you wanted to actually rotate the vector in
the right direction so you you normalize the vectors and then computer normalize
Euclidean distance and that's basically what this does and what this does is
that it for positive cases it tries to make the vectors as aligned with each
other as possible and for negative pairs it tries to make the cosine smaller than
the particular margin the margin in that case which should probably be something
that kind of is close to zero so you want the the cosine you know in a high
dimensional space there's a lot of space near the equator of the sphere of the
high dimensions here okay so all your points now are normalized so this here
what you want is samples that are symmetrically similar to you should be
close to you the samples that are dissimilar should be orthogonal you
don't want them to be Oppo opposed because there is only one point in the
South Pole whereas on the equator is a very very high large space the entire
sphere minus one dimension basically okay so you can make the margin just you
know some small so small positive value and and then you get the entire equator
essentially of this here which contains you almost the entire volume of the
sphere and I dimension since you see loss this is a little more
complicated because that's a task that is basically uses structure prediction
what's called structure prediction so this is I sort of briefly talked about
it very quickly a few weeks ago was something very similar to this so this
is it also is applicable when you your output is a sequence of vectors and
scores where the vectors correspond to scores of categories okay and so you
have so your system computes a vector of such score so imagine for example speech
recognition system speech recognition system every 10 milliseconds gives you a
vector of probabilities for what the sound being pronounced right now is and
the number of categories usually is quite large on the order of a few
thousand okay so give you basically a softmax vector of a size you know
typically three thousand let's say one of those every 10 milliseconds all right
and what you like you know you have a desired output and the desired output is
what word was being pronounced and a word that's being pronounced that
corresponds to kind of a particular sequence of sounds if you want that you
might you might know so what you need now is a course that basically is row if
that sequence looks like like that sequence but what you might allow is for
the input sequence to repeat some of the sounds if you want right so so for
example you know my my cost to make the target might be the word seven they say
and it's pronounced really quickly 7 so you basically have you know a very small
number of samples of each sound in the sequence but then perhaps the the person
who is pronouncing the the word now that user as a training sample pronounced it
very slowly like seven right so now the the first the first takes you know
several several frames of 10 milliseconds that should all be mapped
to the the same instance of the earth in the indian foot
and i do that picture before but i gonna do it again right so the you have let's
see you have a sequence of scores coming out of soft max's let's say it's
actually better if there are energies but firstly TC they need to be and then
you have the target sequence and i think of this as some sort of matrix and each
entry in that matrix basically measures the distance between the two vectors
that are here okay so when i'm treating the matrix indicates how this vector
looks like that vector for example with the course entropy or something like
that okay or is quite error it doesn't matter what the last function is so now
if this is the word seven pronounced slowly okay and this has perhaps only
one instance of each sound you want all of those you know you would want all of
those vectors corresponding to the e to be mapped to that vector here okay so
you want to compute that cost of you know confusing that those all of those I
mean map matching those ease to that to that
e now of course here the system could use the correct answer so you don't have
much of a problem but if the target is seven but the word that was pronounced
here or the output that was produced by the system does not correspond to seven
that's that's that's when you run into into trouble so
here what you do is you find the best mapping from the input sequence to the
output sequence okay so the s gets mapped to the s the e to the e the V to
the V the east to the e and the end to the N so you get this kind of path if
you want that think of this as a path in the graph
and the way you determine this is basically by using a dynamic programming
algorithm the short path algorithm that figures out how do I get from here to
here you know path that minimizes the sum of the distance distances between
the the all the vectors of the distances between the vectors of you know all the
points are going through ok so there's a optimization respect to a latent
variable if you want okay and CGC basically decide for you right so you
give it two sequences and it computes the distance between them and you know
kind of the best kind of mapping between the two by allowing basically to to map
multiple input vectors to kind of a single one on the output it cannot
expand it it can only kind of reduce if you want and then that's done in a way
that you can back propagate gradient to it we'll come back to this two more
things like this at the end if you can oops so this is what this the target is
assumed to be many-to-one the alignment of the input to the target is assumed to
be miniature when which leave is the length of the target sequence such that
it must be smaller than the length of the input that's for the reason I just
explained okay so it's basically differentiable time-warping you could
think of it this way or sort of a module that does that any time marking or
dynamic programming and it's still differentiable the idea for this goes
back in the early 90s in the Lobo two species actually that's very old very a
good paper or resource to learn more about that dynamic programming algorithm
there actually that's kind of what I'm gonna talk about next I may not have
time to go through it but I'll try to okay but basically the last
part of the energy based model tutorial okay
so the initial base model tutorial the 2006 paper that we give you a reference
a link to a tutorial on energy based models the this the second part is all
about this kind of stuff essentially okay so it's more energy based models
but now in getting more of a supervised context if you want
so preliminary so before I get to this I want to come back to the sort of more
general formulation of energy based models and the idea that so if you want
to kind of define energy based models in the proper way these are the conditional
versions you have a a training set a bunch of pairs x y y I for I equals 1 to
P you have a loss function also the last functional L of ENS so it takes the
energy function computed by the system okay and the training set and it gives
you a scalar value now you can you can think of this as a functional functional
is a function of a function ok but in fact because the energy function itself
is parametrized by parameter W you can turn this functional into a loss
function which is not just a function of W another function of the energy
function okay and of course the the set of energy functions is called epsilon
here it's family tries by the parameter W which is taken within the set so
training consistent of course minimizing the the loss function or with respect to
W and finding the W that minimizes it and and so one question you might ask
yourself you know I went to a whole bunch of objective function loss
functions here and the question is if you are in an energy based framework
what loss functions are good ones and what all functions are bad ones how do
you characterize a loss function that actually will do something useful for
you ok so here is a general formulation of the
last function it's it's an average over training samples so here I'm kind of
assuming that it's invariant under permutation of the samples so an average
is as good as any other aggregation go-getting function so it's the average
of our training samples of a person for loss function capital L and it takes the
desired answer Y which could be just a category or it could be a whole image or
whatever and it takes the energy function where X the X variable X I is
is equal to X I the ice training sample the Y variable is undetermined okay so e
of W Y and X I is basically the entire shape of the energy function for values
of Y over values of Y for a given X okay X equal to X I and you can have a
regularizer if you want okay so here this is a loss functional again again of
course we have to design this loss function all so that it makes the energy
of correct answers small and the energy of incorrect answers large in some ways
right ok now we're going to go through a bunch of different types of loss
functions so one thing we could do is say my loss function is just going to be
the energy of the correct answer so I'm gonna place myself in the context of
energy based model my system produces scores I interpret those scores as
energies so high is bad good is good that means low is good as opposed to
positive scores and what I'm just going to do is define my energy functional as
unfortunately the energy function of the function of Y as simply the energy that
my model gives to the correct answer okay so basically I give it an X and I
give it the correct answer Y and as a system what energy do you give to that
pair and then I try to make that energy as small as possible okay so you have
this landscape of energy is here now we honor I showed you this
slide in the context of unsupervised super Ronnie here I'm showing to you in
the context of supervised Ronnie so imagine that one of the variables is X
and the other variable is y okay and the blue beads are training samples and you
want to make the energy of the blue beads as far as possible so you're
pulling down on the blue beads but you're not doing anything else and so as
a result depending on the architecture or your network if your network is not
designed properly or if it's designing a bit in no particular way it could very
well be that the energy function is going to become flat everywhere okay
you're just trying to make the energy of the correct answer small are you not
telling the system the energy of everything else should be higher and so
the system might just collapse all right so energy loss is not good in
that sense but there are certain situations where it's applicable because
if the shape of the energy function is such that it cannot make the you can
only make the energy of a single answer small all the other ones being larger
then you need to have a quadratic term okay and we've seen this in the context
of supervised learning people are completely lost about the loss
functional right okay so this is a function Al and it's a function of
another function e okay so it's called a functional because it's
a function of a function right it's not a function of a point it's a function of
a function now if that second function is permit rised by a parameter W then
you can say that the last function is actually a function of that parameter W
now it becomes a regular function okay that's what I had can you can you write
it down it's basically written here okay you can
either write the functional as if I can find it as L of e and s so that's a
functional because it's a function of e which itself is a function okay but e
itself is a function of W and so if I write the last function directly as a
function of W now it's just a regular function
okay yeah I mean I asked the question that was asked in the chat I yeah I was
kind of you I know before that you know for okay we've seen the negative log
likelihood loss before I talked about this so this is a loss function that
tries to make the energy of the correct answer so look at the rectangle in red
tries to make the energy of the correct answer as low as possible and then you
have the second term whatever beta log sum over all why's of e to the minus
beta e of WI X and this one is trying to make the energy of all Y's for this
given X as large as possible okay because the best way to make this term
small is to make those energies large because they enter in there as a
negative of negative its financial okay so this has this kind of pushing down on
the correct answer pushing up on incorrect answer behavior and we've seen
before we just talked about margin loss and and other types of losses here is
something that's called a perceptron loss because it's basically very similar
to I mean it's exactly the same as the loss that was used for the perceptron 60
years ago over 60 years ago so this one says I want to make the energy of the
correct answer small and the same time I want to make the energy of the smallest
the smallest energy for all answers as large as possible okay so pick the Y
that has the smallest energy in your system make that as large as you can the
same time picks the correct energy make that as small as you can now there is a
point at which the answer with the correct energy is going
to equal to the correct answer and so that difference can never be negative
okay because the first term is necessarily one term in that minimum and
so the difference is at best zero and for every other cases is in spot this
trick is positive it's only zero when the system gives you the correct answer
okay but this objective function does not prevent the system from giving the
very same energy to every answer okay so in that sense it's a bad energy it's a
bad loss function so bad a loss function because it it says I want the energy of
the correct answer to be small I want the energy of all the other answers to
be large but I don't insist that there is any difference between them so the
system can choose to make every answer the same energy and that's a class okay
so the spectrum loss is not good it's actually only good for linear systems
but it's not good for as a objective function for nonlinear systems so here
is a way to design an objective function that will always be good and you you
take the energy of the correct answer and you take the energy of the most
offending incorrect answer which means the value of y that is incorrect but at
the same time is the lowest energy of all the incorrect answers okay and your
system will work if that difference is negative in other words if the energy of
the correct answer is smaller than the energy of the most of any correct answer
but at least some quantity some margin okay so as long as your objective
function will you design it ensures that the energy of the correct answer is
smaller than the energy of the most of any correct answer by at least a margin
nonzero margin then you'll find your loss function is good okay so things
like kyndra's are good the heat loss basically says and we talked about this
just just before I want the energy of the correct answer to be smaller than
the energy of the most offending incorrect
which is denoted why I bar here but at least M okay this is what this house
function does it's a hinge loss and it wants to push down the energy of this
guy below the energy of that guy by at least this margin so this has a margin M
and this will you know if you train a system with this loss a well and he can
run the task he will run the task and probably produce the good answers the
heat loss the soft hinge loss which is in the context of Nigeria's models is
expressed this way basically instead of feeling the difference between the
All right, so we're going to talk about two or three topics today,
and the first one is going to be kind of a review of some of the functions that exist in Pytorch.
And kind of when and how to use them.
So, the first set of topics is about activation functions,
and there is a whole bunch of them defined in Pytorch,
and they basically come from, you know, various papers that people have written
where they claim that this or that particular objective function or activation function works better for their problem.
So, of course, everybody knows the ReLU.
That's very standard one, but there's lots of variations of ReLUs.
These ReLUs where the bottom part is not constant and set to zero.
but it can be allowed to change either only with the positive slope or force to be to have a negative slope,
or sometimes being random in the case of the randomized Leaky ReLU.
So, they have, you know, nice names like Leaky ReLU, PReLU, RReLU, random ReLU, etc.
So, Leaky ReLU is one where you allow the bottom part to have slight negative slope.
and that kind of prevents the issue that sometimes pops up that you know,
when ReLU is off, it doesn't get any gradient.
So, here you get a chance for that system that function to actually propagate gradient,
and perhaps do something useful can go all the way to kind of compete for ratification of the signal,
kind of like an absolute value if you want.
PReLU is one .... yeah, go ahead.
The previous activation was is user using the discriminator in a GAN,
such that we always have gradients going backward for the generator,
and also this activation was necessary in order to train the very skinny network.
I show at the beginning of the class because again having like a very very skinny network,
it was basically impossible to get gradients flowing back,
because we were like ending up in one of the quadrants without, you know, where everything was zero out,
and then nothing would have been actually trained if you wouldn't have use, you know, this activation function
that allows me to get some kind of gradients
even if we are in the regions where we are trying to suppress the output.
So, yeah, right.
So, PReLU is fairly similar except that now the slope and the negative side can be just about anything.
And okay, what's interesting about those all those functions that we just saw is that they are scale-invariant
in the sense that they, you know, you can multiply the signal by two and the output will not be changed.
Yeah, I mean it would be multiplied, by two but otherwise unchanged, so they are equivalent to scale.
There's no sort of intrinsic scale in those functions, right?
Because there's only one non-linearity, and it's a sharp one.
So
Now we're getting into functions where the scale matters.
So, the amplitude of the incoming signal will affect the type of non-linearity that you're going to get,
and one of those is the Softplus.
So, Softplus is sort of a differentiable version of ReLU if you want.
It's kind of the soft version of positive part,
and it's usually parameterized as you can see at the top here.
1/ * log( 1+ exp(*X) )
So it's kind of like the log sum exponential that we've been using a lot for supervised purpose, except here.
One of the terms in the sum is equal to 1 which is kind of like exponential zero if you want.
So, that looks like kind of a function that sort of asymptotically is the identity function for large positive values,
and asymptotically zero for negative values.
So, approximates the ReLU.
It has a scale parameter though, this parameter,
The larger , the more the function will look like a ReLU.
So the kink, the corner, will be kind of sharper if goes to infinity.
But that function has a scale.
Now, you can parameterize those functions in various ways,
and this is sort of a another example of kind of a soft version of ReLU if you want
where here you use ReLU as a basis, something that you add a small constant to it, that kind of makes it smooth.
You know, I can't tell you that any of those has any particular advantage over the others.
It really depends on the problem, but they all have kind of similar properties if you want.
This also you can make sort of continuously closer to ReLU.
That's yet
Okay, so when difference here, in this case, is that
this guy actually goes negative. Right?
So, unlike the ReLU that has its minimum at zero, it's horizontal asymptote at zero, this guy goes below zero.
And that may or may not be advantageous depending on the application you have.
Sometimes it's advantageous because it allows the system to basically makes the average of the output zero
which is advantageous for certain types of gradient descent convergence.
The weights that are connected to units like this will see both positive and negative values
which will then converge faster than if they only see positive values.
So, it's been the same here, and it's just kind of a differently,
you know, a different parametrization of kind of the same thing if you want
with different properties.
So, of course, there's tons of variations of this, you know with various parameters with different properties,
and, you know, some of them that have particular properties that can relate them to gaussian distributions,
for example, this is not the cumulative distribution of a gaussian, but ...
Okay, so those were things that have one kinks in them,
and if the kink is sharp, there's no scale.
If the kink has some scale in it, there is some scale, but it's still sort of a single kink non-linearity.
Now, we're getting into nonlinearities that have two kinks.
Okay, so this one is basically a saturating ReLU.
I don't show why saturates at 6, you know, why not?
But, you know, why not parameterize this a little better,
so, here's a smooth function that you're familiar with
because it's used in Recurrent Nets, in Gated Recurrent Nets, in LSTM, in Softmax.
You know, basically, this is a two-way Softmax. You can think of it this way.
and this is just a function that goes kind of smoothly between 0 & 1.
It's sometimes called a Fermi-Dirac function as well because it derives from some work in physics, in statistical physics.
And then there is the hyperbolic tangent that we also talked about.
It's basically identical to the Sigmoid except it's centered.
So, it goes between -1 and +1 and it's a little
you know, it's twice the amplitude and the gain is a little different, but it plays the same role.
The advantage of hyperbolic tangent is that the output is you can expect the output to not have zero mean, but be close to having zero mean,
and again, that's advantageous for the weights that follow
because they see positive and negative values, and they tend to converge faster, that's the case.
So, I used to be a big fan of those.
Unfortunately, if you stack a lot of Sigmoids in many layers in a neural net,
you can attend to not learn very efficiently.
You have to be very careful about normalization if you want the system to converge if you have many layers.
So, in that sense, the single kink functions are better for deeper networks.
So, it's Softsign, this is basically a bit like the Sigmoid except that it doesn't get to the asymptotes as fast,
so, it doesn't get stuck towards the asymptote as quickly.
So, one problem with hyperbolic tangent and the Sigmoid is that we get close to the asymptote,
the gradient goes to zero fairly quickly.
And so, if the weights of a unit become too large,
they kind of saturate this unit, and the gradients get very small,
and then the unit doesn't learn very quickly anymore.
It's a problem that exists both, sorry, both in Sigmoids and hyperbolic tangent.
And so, SoftSign is a function of that was proposed by Yoshua Bengio and some his collaborators,
and it kind of saturates slower, and so it doesn't have that same problem.
I mean it has the problem also, but not to the same extent.
Okay, and this is kind of the opposite hard tangent, Hardtanh,
I don't know if it deserves that name, but it's basically just a ramp, okay?
And that works surprisingly well, particularly, if your weights are somehow kept within a kind of small value.
So, the units don't saturate too much.
It's surprisingly how well it works, and you know, people use this in supervised context.
But that's sort of, you know, non-standard.
so hard threshold is very rarely used because you can't really propagate gradient to it.
Okay? and this is really what kept people from inventing backprop in the 60s and 70s
which is that they were using binary neurons, and so they didn't think of the whole idea of gradients because of that.
Okay, those other functions are rarely used in the context of neural nets,
or at least for kind of activation function in a traditional neural net.
They used mostly for sometimes for things like sparse coding.
So, one step in sparse coding consists in to compute the value of the latent variable,
consist in shrinking all the values in the latent variable in the agent vector by some value,
and you do this with a shrinkage function.
This is kind of a soft version of shrinkage function, the hard version is here.
I mean, it's called Soft Shrink, but it actually has corners in it.
The reason it's called soft shrink is because there is a hard shrink that looks different. We show it you in a minute.
So, this basically just changes a variable by a constant toward zero. Right?
and if it goes below zero, it climbs at zero, if it's brought too long.
And this is basically just the identity function to which you subtract hyperbolic tangent to make it look like a shrink.
Basically, if we try to get the whatever value close to zero, they actually are forced to zero basically, right?
Right. So, small values are forced to zero, others are shrunk toward zero,
but you know, since they are large enough, they're not going to get to zero.
So, again that's used mostly as, you know, you can think of it as a step of gradient for an L1 criterion.
Okay?
So, if you have a variable, you have an L1 cost function on it,
and you take a step in the negative gradient of the L1, so L1 cost is an absolute value.
This will cause the variable to kind of go towards zero by a constant which is the slope of that L1 criterion,
and to kind of stay at zero, you know coming from either side, it doesn't kind of overshoot if you want
and so that's the non-linear function you will use,
and that's one of the steps in the EAST algorithm that is used for inference in sparse coding.
But again, it's rarely used in sort of regular neural nets,
unless your encoder is kind of used as kind of a estimation of sparse coding.
This is the hard shrink, so hard shrink basically climbs every value smaller than to zero, Okay?
So, if a value is smaller than or larger than -, then sort of between - and , and is some constant is just set it to zero.
Again, it's used for things like, you know, certain types of sparse coding, but rarely as an activation function in the neural net.
So, LogSigmoid is mostly used in cost functions not really as an activation function either,
but it's a useful function to have if you want to plug this into a loss function, and we'll see that in a minute.
So, Softmin we've seen this is the same as Softmax except you have minus signs, so this is sort of more ...
So, those are multi-dimensional non-linearities. All right?
You have a vector in and you get a vector out which is at same size as the input vector,
and we know about Softmax is you know exponential Xi divided by sum over j exponential Xj,
this is Softmin where you put a minus sign in front of the X.
So, you view the X as if you want as energies instead of scores, as penalties instead of scores.
It's a good way of turning a bunch of numbers to something that looks a bit like a probability distribution, which means numbers between 0 and 1 that sum to 1,
and that's the Softmax which we all know.
So, Log Softmax again, it's not very much used as a non-linearity within the neural net,
but it's used a lot at the output as kind of one piece of a loss function, it will see this in a minute.
Okay. So, those ...
Questions. Yes. We have a question.
So, for PReLU, I'm not sure I understand number one, why we want the same value for all channels?
and number two, how learning "a" would actually be advantageous?
You could have a different "a" for different channels.
So, different units can have a different "a" it could be used this as a parameter of every unit or not, it could be shared.
That's gonna up to you.
It could be shared at the level of a feature map in the convolutional net,
or it could be shareed on all future maps, or it could be individual to every unit.
If you really want to preserve the convolutional nature of a convolutional net,
you probably want to have the same "a" for every unit in the future map,
but you couldn't have different a's for different feature maps.
Okay. What was the second question?
Why learning actually specific value would be advantageous like why are we learning "a"?
You can learn it or not, you can fix it.
The reason for fixing it would be, you know, not necessarily to kind of have sort of more powerful non-linearity,
but to kind of ensure that the non-linearity gives you a non-zero gradient, even if it's in the negative region.
So, you know, learnable not learnable.
So, to make it learnable allows the system to basically turn a non-linearity into either the linear mapping,
which of course is not particularly interesting, but why not,
ReLU or something like a full rectification,
Okay? where "a" would be -1 in the negative part,
which, you know, can be interesting for certain types of application.
So, for example, if you have a convolutional net that has an edge-detector, an edge-detector as a polarity, right?
It's got plus coefficients on one side minus coefficients on the other side.
And so, it's gonna react. So, if you have an edge in an image that goes from say Dark to Bright,
the, you know, the convolution will react positively to this one,
but if you have another edge from, you know, in the opposite direction,
then the filter will react negatively.
Now, if you want your filter to react to an edge regardless of its polarity, you rectify it.
Okay? so that would be kind of just absolute value.
Now, you could, of course, ??? ??? ??? in have to use a PReLU, you can just use the absolute value.
Probably a better idea is to use a square actually.
So, you take the square of square non-linearity.
It's not implemented as kind of a neural net non-linearity,
but, you know, in the functional form of Pytorch you just write square, and that's it.
Hope answered the question. Any other question on this topic?
I have a question, it seems to me like these non-linearities are trying to basically make a linear function non-linear,
and the tweak in the lines denote like the change in that function.
So, can we think of this as if we want to model of curve in the line,
should we have learnable parameters on both, like before the 0 and after the 0 on the x-axis?
Well. So, yeah. I mean there is diminishing return.
So, the question is, you know, how complex do you want your non-linearity to be?
So, you could imagine of course parameterizing an entire non-linear function,
you know with spline parameters or Bayesian curves or something like this right.
Or, I don't know, Chebyshev polynomials,
you know, I mean, you can parameterize any mapping you want, right?
You can imagine those parameters could be part of the learning process.
However, you know, what is the advantage of doing this versus just you know having more units in your system?
and relying on the fact that multiple units will be added in the end to approximate the function you want?
Generally, it really depends on what like,
if you want to do regression in a fairly low dimensional space, so perhaps you want some parameterize non-linearities, that might help.
You might want to have a collection of different non-linearities with maybe things like Chebyshev polynomials,
if you want to do a good approximations.
But for like, you know, high-dimensional tasks like image recognition or things like this,
you just want a non-linearity, and it works better if the non-linearity is monotonic.
Otherwise, it creates all kinds of issues because you could have two points that will produce the same output,
and so it will ambiguous for the system to learn the right function there.
So you want it, it's much better if the function is monotonic, and almost all the functions here are monotonic,
except if you have a negative "a" here in the PReLU case.
So it's a big advantage to having monotonic functions.
But in principle, you could parameterize, you know, any function you want.
People are played with this, you know. They're not very popular,
because mostly they don't seem to be bringing a huge advantage in the kind of applications that people use a large neural nets for.
Other questions?
Another question is going to be kink converge smooth?
Yeah.
Do we have any application with the choice of non-linearities made of ??? ???,
the only thing I'm aware of is using a single ??? function ??? double kink for deep neural networks ???? in better?
Well, so here's a party with double kink, double kink has a built-in scale in it,
which means if the weights of the incoming layer are multiplied by 2, or the signal amplitude is multiplied by 2,
the result on the output would be completely different, right?
because you will be, you know, the signal would be more in the non-linearity.
So, you'll get completely different behavior of your layer,
whereas if you have a function with only one kink, if you multiply the input by 2 with the output get also multiplied by 2,
in a module of bias, but the signal of the bias is fine.
What I meant to ask is taken of a situation with a choice of activation function made a big difference in the performance of the model?
except for the deep networks using ReLU instead of Sigmoid?
There is no sort of general answer to this.
Like if you're going to use attention,
you have to use Softmax. I mean you have no choice, right?
I mean, it's not like you have to use Softmax,
but you want to have something where you get coefficients, right, to kind of focus the attention of the system on,
or to kind of spread the attention of the system,
and not allow it to cheat which is to pay attention to multiple things at one time,
you have to have some sort of normalization of the coefficients that come out of the attention system, right?
So, normally in most attention systems like in transformers and stuff,
the coefficients are passed through a Softmax,
so you get a bunch of coefficients that are between 0 & 1, and sum to 1.
And so that causes the system to have to pay attention to, you know, a small number of things,
so it can only concentrate the coefficients on a small number of items.
And it has to spread it, right?
The other ways to do normalization you can do...
and in fact, there is something that's wrong with Softmax normalization for transformers or for attention,
which is that if you want a coefficient coming out with Softmax to be close to zero,
you need the input to be close to minus infinity (-)
Okay? or to be a considerably smaller than the largest one, right?
When you go into the Softmax,
one output, the largest input is going to cause the corresponding output to be large.
If you want that output to be close to 1, and all the other ones to be close to 0,
you basically want this input to be extremely large,
and all the other ones to be large and negative. Okay?
Now, you know, that can be a problem when the what you are computing at the input are dot products
because the result is that, you know, the easiest way for a system to produce a small dot product is
to have two vectors that are orthogonal to each other which gives the dot product to zero.
If you insist that the dot product should be very very small,
then either you have to make the, so you have to make the two vectors basically point in opposite directions,
and you have to make them very long.
And that's not so great.
And so, using softmax for attention basically limits the contrast that you're gonna have
between the coefficients which is not necessarily a good thing.
So, you know, same thing for LSTM, Gated Recurrent Nets, etc,
you need Sigmoids there because you need coefficients that are between 0 and 1,
you know, that either we set the memory cell or make it a ????
So that, it keeps it, so it's previous memory or kind of write the new input in it.
So there, it's nice to have an output that varies continuously between 0 and 1.
Then you have no choice.
So I mean, I don't think you can say just, you know, in generic term,
you know, this non-linearity is better than the other one.
There are certain cases where it learns better,
there are certain cases where it relieves you from having to initialize properly,
there is certain cases where it works better if you have lots of layers
like you know, single kink functions work better if you have lots of layers better than Sigmoid like functions.
There's no kind of, there is no single answer, basically.
I have a question just regarding the general differences between a non-linear activation that has kinks versus a smooth non-linear activation.
Yeah
Is there sort of any general reason or rule to why we would prefer to have kinks in the function or not?
It's a matter of scale-invariant of scale equivalence. So if the kink is hard,
again, you multiply the input by 2, the output is multiplied by 2, but otherwise unchanged, okay?
If you have a smooth transition, if you multiply the input by let's say 100,
the output now will look like you had a hard kink.
okay, because the smooth part now is become shrunk by a factor of 100.
if you divide the input by 100, now, the kink becomes a very very smooth sort of convex functions.
Okay, so it changes the behavior by changing the scale the input you change the behavior of the unit,
and that might be a problem sometimes,
because when you train a multi-layer neural net,
and you have two layers that are one after the other,
you don't have a good control for like how big the weights of this layer are relative to that other weights.
So imagine you have a two layer network where you don't have a non-linearity in the middle,
so the system is completely linear, right?
If the network has arrived at a solution,
you can multiply the incoming the first layer weight matrix by 2 divide the second weight matrix by 2,
and overall the network will have exactly the same output.
Okay? you won't have changed anything.
And what that means is that when you do training,
there is nothing that forces the system to have a particular scale for the weight matrices.
All right?
So, now, if you put a non-linearity in the middle,
and you still don't have it because train for the system to kind of,
you know, have scales for the first layer weight versus the second layer weight
that, you know, you'd better have a non-linearity that doesn't care about scale.
Okay?
So, if you have non-linearity that does care about scale,
then your network doesn't have a choice of what size weight matrix it can use in the first layer,
because that will completely change the behavior,
and it may want to have large weights for some other reason which will saturate the non-linearity
and then kind of create, you know, vanishing gradient issues.
So, it's not entirely clear.
You know, what? Why is it that? you know, did networks work better with single kink functions,
but it's probably due to that scale-invariant property or scale equivalence property.
Now, there would be other ways of fixing this problem,
which would be to basically set a hard scale on the weights of every layer.
so you couldn't like normalize the weights of the layers.
so that, the variance that of things that's going to unit, you know, it's always constant.
In fact, that's a little bit what batch normalization does,
or the various normalization schemes, they do that to some extent,
you know, they put the mean at zero, and the variance is constant.
So, now, the variance of the amplitude of the output doesn't depend on the size of the weights because it's normalized.
So, you know that is partially why things like batch norm and group norm and things like this help
is because they can fix the scale a little bit,
but then, if you fix the scale, then with something like batch norm,
the system now doesn't have any way of choosing which part of the non-linearity it's going to use in the two kink function system.
Okay, so things like group normalization or batch normalization are incompatible with kind of Sigmoids if you want.
??? a Sigmoid, you don't want normalization just before it.
See, that provides some really good intuition. Thank you.
Okay, any other question others?
I have one more question. I noticed in a Softmax function some people use the temperature coefficient.
So, in what cases would we want to use their temperature? And why would we use it?
Well, so to some extent the temperature is redundant with incoming weights.
So, if you have weighted sum's coming into your Softmax,
you know, having parameter in your Softmax equal to 2 instead of 1
is the same as just making your weights twice as big, it has exactly the same effect.
Okay, so that parameter is redundant with the size of the weights.
But again, if you are or the size of the weighted sum the variance of the weighted sum if you want
but again, if you have a batch normalization in there, then the temperature parameter matters,
because now the input variances are fixed.
So now, the temperature matters.
Temperature basically controls how hard, you know, the distribution on the output will be.
So, with a very very large , you basically will have one of the outputs equal to 1,
and all the other ones very close to 0.
I mean very close to 1 and very close to 0 where is small than this softer,
in the limited equal to 0, it's more like an average actually that you get like Softmax behaves a little bit like an average.
So, you know, goes to infinity, it so behaves a bit like argMax,
and goes to 0, it behaves a bit like an average.
So if you have some sort of normalization before the Softmax,
then tuning this parameter allows you to control this kind of hardness.
And what people do sometimes in certain scenarios is that they start with a relatively low ,
So that, the numbers that are produced are kind of soft.
So, you get gradients everywhere, you know, it's kind of well-behaved in terms of gradient descent.
And then as learning proceeds, if you want kind of harder decisions in your attention mechanism or whatever, you increase .
And so that makes the system kind of make harder decisions.
It doesn't learn as well anymore, but it's you know, presumably after a few iterations, it's kind of in the right ballpark.
So, you can sort of sharpen the decisions there by can be increasing .
It's useful for example in a mixture of experts,
and you know, self attention systems are kind of you can think of as a weird form of mixture of experts.
So, a mixture of experts, you know, you have multiple sub networks,
and their outputs are can linearly combine with coefficients that are
the output of the Softmax itself could, you know, controlled by another neural net.
So, if you want kind of a soft mixture, you have a low ,
and as you increase to infinity, basically, you're going to select one of the experts and ignore all the other ones.
That might be useful, for example, if you want to train a mixture of experts or an attention mechanism,
but in the end, you want to safe computation by just determining which expert do I need to compute and just not computing the other ones.
So, in that case you want those coefficients to be basically either 1 or 0,
and you can train the system progressively to do this by increasing .
The physicists have a name for this,
because it uses kind of tricks or various other things, that's called annealing.
It has the same meaning as, so annealing comes from metalwork, right?
You're making a steel or something, and you make a sword or something, right?
And you heat it up, and then you cool it.
And depending on whether you cool it quickly or slowly,
you change the crystal instructure of the metal,
so this idea of annealing of progressively lowering the temperature correspond to this increasing this .
is like an inverse temperature, it's akin to an inverse temperature.
Any other question?
I think we are good.
All right. Okay. So next topic is Loss Functions.
So, Pytorch has a whole bunch of loss functions as you might have seen.
And of course there are things are simple ones like mean square error.
So, I don't need to explain to you what it is, you know compute the square of the error between the desired output Y, and actually input X,
and if it's already be batched with n samples, then you have you know n losses,
one for each of the samples in the batch .
and you can tell this loss function to either keep that vector or to kind of reduce it by computing mean or sum.
Okay, pretty simple.
Here's a different loss, that's the L1 loss.
So, this is basically the absolute value of the difference between the desired output and the actual output,
and you want to use this to do what's called "robust regression".
So, if you want small errors to count a lot and large errors to count but you know not as much as if you use the square,
perhaps because you have noise in your data, so you know that you have a bunch of data points.
You're trying to kind of train a neural net or something to kind of, you know, fit a curve or, you know, do regression,
but you know, that you have a few outliers,
so you have a few points there are, you know, very far away from what they should be
just because you know the system has noise or something, or the data was collected with some noise.
So, you want the system to be robust to that noise,
you don't want the cost function to increase too quickly as the points are far away from, you know, the kind of the general curve.
So, L1 loss would be more robust.
Now, the problem with the L1 loss is that it's not differentiable at the bottom,
and so, you know, you have to kind of be careful when you get to the bottom of how you do the gradient
that's basically done with the soft shrink essentially that's the gradient of L1 loss.
Now, to correct for that people have come up with various ways of kind of making the L1 loss for bias for large losses,
but then still smooth at the bottom kind of behaving like squared error at the bottom.
So, an example of this is particular function, Smooth L1 Loss.
It's basically L1 far away and it's sort of L2 nearby,
and that presents sometimes that's called a Huber loss.
Some people call this also elastic Network because this ...
an old paper from the 1980s or 1990s that kind of proposed this kind of objective function for different purpose.
So, that's useful that was advertised by Ross Girshick at Fast R-CNN paper for ...
and it's used quite a bit in computer vision for supervised purposes.
Again, it's for protecting against outliers.
This is also sharper results, now when we do like image prediction?
sharper than?
using the MSE.
Not particularly, I mean it's just like the MSE for small errors, okay?
So, that doesn't make any difference,
but it doesn't, or maybe I misunderstood what your point was.
Sorry, I was trying to compare the L1 versus the L2 that L2 gives us like usually blurry predictions
whenever we try it to do prediction by using like the minimizing the L2,
whereas like people are minimizing the L1 in order to have like sharper overall predictions.
Okay, so if you take a bunch of points, okay?
if you take a bunch of Y values, okay, and you ask the question, what value ...
So, you take a bunch of points on Y, Okay?
Yeah, you ask the question what value of Y minimizes the square loss?
The answer is the average of all the Y's. Okay?
Okay, so if you, so if for a single X you have a whole bunch of Y which means you have noise in your data,
your system will want to produce the average of all the Y's that you're observing.
Okay, and if the Y you're observing is not a single value, but is I don't know an image,
the average of a bunch of images is a blurry image, okay?
that's why you get those blurry effects.
Now, with L1, the value of Y that minimizes the L1 norm, the L1 distance,
so, basically the sum of the absolute values of the differences between the value you're considering and all the points, all the Y's points,
that's the median.
Okay, so it's a given point.
All right?
uh-huh, I see.
Median of course is not blurry, it's just an image.
Although it's kind of difficult to define in multiple dimensions, but ...
So, one problem with this loss is that it has a scale, right?
So, here the transition here is at point 5, but why should it be at point 5?
You know, it could be it depends what the scale of your errors are.
Okay.
Negative log likelihood loss, this is really not the negative log likelihood loss.
I'm not sure why it's called this way in Pytorch,
but basically here imagine that you have an X vector coming out.
Okay, and your loss function is there is one correct X.
So imagine each X correspond to a score for multi-class classification.
So, you have a desired class, which is one particular index in that vector.
Okay? Now, what you want is you want to make that score as large as possible.
Okay? If those scores are likelihoods,
then this is minimum negative log likelihood, if those scores are log likelihoods.
And this is maximum likelihood or minimum negative log likelihood.
Okay, but there is nothing in this module that actually specifies that the L has to be log likelihoods.
So, this is just you know, make my desired component as large as possible. That's it.
If you put negative signs in front, so now you can interpret the X's as energies as opposed to scores.
Okay, they're not positive scores. They're like penalties if you want, but it's the same.
So, the formula here says, you know, just pick the X that happens to be the correct one for one sample in the batch,
and make that score as large as possible.
Now, this particular one allows you to give a different weight to different categories,
which is those W's, it's a weight vector that gives a weight to each of the categories.
It's useful in a lot of cases particularly if you have widely different frequencies for the categories,
you might want to increase the weight of samples for which you have a small number of examples.
I mean for categories for which you have a small number of samples.
However, I'm actually not a big fan of this.
I think it's a much better idea to just increase the frequency of the samples from the classes, you know, that appears rarely.
So that, you equalize the frequency, the frequencies of the classes when you train.
It's much better because it exploits stochastic gradient in a better way. Okay?
So, bottom line of that is if you have ...
let me actually draw a picture of this.
So, let's say you have a problem where you have tons of samples for category 1,
and then the small number of samples for category 2,
and a tiny number of samples for category 3.
You could, so let's say
you know, here you have, I don't know, 1000 samples,
and here you have 500 samples,
and here you have, I don't know, 200 samples, right?
So, you could do is using this kind of weight function.
You could give this a weight of 1, and this guy weight of 2, and this guy weight of 5.
And then you can equalize the weights if you want.
It's really better to make sure that the weights normalized to 1 that would be probably a better idea.
But what I recommend is not that.
What I recommend is when you pick your samples,
you basically pick one sample from class 1, and then one sample from class 2, and one sample from class 3.
and then you know you keep doing this during your training session,
and when you get to the end of class 3 you go back to the beginning.
Okay?
So, you keep going here, but here you go back to the first sample.
Keep going here, go back, and now you have the second sample.
Okay? And now you get to the end of class 2, go back to the start.
Okay? So, the next sample is going to be here
here and here.
And then the next one here here and here.
Here here, and then this guy wraps around again, etc.
Right? So, you basically have equal probability equal frequencies, for all the categories
by just going through those kind of circular buffers, more often for categories for which you have fewer samples.
Okay?
One thing you should absolutely never do is equalize the frequencies by just not using all the samples in categories that are frequent,
I mean that's horrible. You should never let any data on the floor.
There's never any reason to leave that on the floor. Okay?
Now here is a problem with this.
The problem with this is that after you've trained your neural net that to do this,
the neural net that does not know about the relative likelihood, the relative frequencies of the samples.
And so let's say this is a system that does medical diagnosis.
It doesn't know that the common cold is very very more frequent than, you know, lung cancer or something, right?
So, what you need to do in the end is do a path a few pathes perhaps where you can fine tune your system,
so that with the actual frequencies of the categories,
and the effect of this is going to be for the system to adapt the biases at the output layer.
So that the likelihood of, you know, a diagnosis corresponds to the frequency of it, right?
It's gonna favor things that are more frequent.
The reason why I don't want to do this during the entire training is because if you train a multi-layer net,
the system basically never develops the right features for rare cases,
and I may have spoken about this already in the class in past weeks,
to kind of recycle the example of medical school,
you don't spend when you go to medical school,
you don't spend time studying the flue that is proportional to the frequency of the flue with respect to very rare diseases, for example, right?
You spend basically the same time studying all the diseases.
In fact, you spend more time studying complicated one, which usually tends to be rarer.
and that's because you need to develop the features for it, okay?
And then you need to kind of correct for the fact that you know, those rare diseases are rare.
So, you don't do that, you know, you don't suspect the diagnosis for rare diseases very often because, you know, it's rare.
Okay.
So that's all for weights.
Cross entropy loss, so you'll be using this a lot of course.
And cross entropy loss is a kind of merging of two things:
merging of log Softmax function, and negative log likelihood loss, okay?
And the reason why you want to have this is for numerical reasons.
So, the log Softmax is, you know, basically the Softmax followed by log, right?
So, you first compute the softmax then you do the log.
If you do Softmax, and then log and you backpropagate through this,
you might have gradients in the middle between the log and the Softmax that end up being infinite.
So, for example, if the maximum value of one of the Softmax is close to 1,
and sum of the other ones are close to 0,
you take the log, you get something that's close to minus infinity.
You backpropagate through the log, you get something that's close to infinity.
Okay? because the slope of log close to zero is very very close to infinity.
But now you multiply this by a Softmax that is saturated.
So, it's multiplied by something that's very close to zero.
So, in the end you get a reasonable number.
But because the intermediate numbers are close to infinity or 0,
you multiply something that's close to plus infinity by something that's close to 0,
you get numerical issues.
So, you don't want to separate log and Softmax, you want to do log SoftMax in one go.
It simplifies the formula, it makes the whole thing much more stable numerically.
And for similar reasons, you also want to merge log Softmax and negative log likelihood loss.
So, basically if you have log Softmax and negative log likelihood loss,
it says I'm gonna a bunch of weighted sums,
I'm gonna pass them through Softmax, I'm gonna take the log of those,
and then I want to make the output of the log Softmax for the correct class as large as possible.
Okay, that's what the negative log likelihood loss does.
It wants to make the score of the correct class as large as possible.
We saw that just a minute ago, right?
when you backpropagate through the log Softmax, as a consequence,
it's gonna make the score of all the other classes as small as possible.
Right? Because of the normalization.
And so that, you know, that's why sometimes the whole idea of sort of building a network by
you know, modules sometimes there is an advantage instead of merging in modules into single one by end.
Right.
So, the cross entropy loss, in fact, this explains a little bit, you know, those numerical simplifications.
So, the loss, you know, takes an X vector and a category, a desired category, a class, Okay?
and computes the negative log of the Softmax applied to the vector of scores,
but the one that's on the numerator here is the X of the index of the correct class
Okay, so that's your loss.
The negative log of exponential the score of the correct class divided by the sum of the exponential's of all the scores.
Okay?
You can think of the X's as negative energies.
It's completely equivalent.
Now, when you do the math and you simplify, the log and the exponential's gonna simplify,
and so you just get the score of the correct class, the negative score of the correct class.
Okay?
So, to make that small, you make the score large,
and then plus the log of the sum of the exponential's of the scores of all the other class to make that small.
You make all the Xj's small, negative as far as, you know, as negative as possible.
Okay, so this will make the score of the correct class large, make the score of everything else small.
Again, like in the ???? you can re-weight per category.
Also, there is a physical interpretation, right? of the cross entropy.
Right. Okay, so why is it called cross entropy?
Because it is the cross entropy between two distributions.
It's the KL divergence really between two distributions.
It doesn't appear clearly here in this formula.
But think of the Softmax applied to the X vector as a distribution, Okay?
So, take the X vectors the scores rather than to a Softmax you get a bunch of numbers between 0 & 1 that sum to 1.
And now you have a desired distribution, and the desired distribution,
the target distribution if you want is Y in which all the wrong categories had 0 and the correct category is 1.
Okay? Now, compute the KL divergence between those two distributions.
Okay, so it's the sum over indices of the correct probability. Okay?
Which is 0 for except for one term.
Times the ratio between the log of the probability that the system produces and the correct probability, which is one. Okay?
So, all of those terms, you know, reduce to kind of a single term which is just the one for which the correct probability term is 1.
Okay? So we end up with this term.
It's just a negative log of the Softmax output for the correct class.
Okay?
We can use this as a cross entropy between the distribution produced by the system,
and the one-hot vector corresponding to the desired distribution if you want. Okay?
So now there is a, there be another kind of more sophisticated version of this,
which would be the actual KL divergence between the distribution produced by the system and a distribution that you propose whatever it is,
a target distribution which now is not binary,
it's not the one-hot vector anymore, but it's just a vector of numbers,
and that's called the KL divergence loss, in fact. It's we'll see it in a minute.
So, KL divergence is a kind of, you know, it's not a distance because it's not symmetric,
but it's a sort of a divergence between discrete distributions.
Okay. So this one is a bit of, kind of a extension if you want of log Softmax,
and it's a version of it that is applicable for very very large categorization,
so if you have many many many categories, what you might want to do is kind of cut some corners;
you don't want to compute the giant Softmax over million categories or maybe even more.
So there you can sort of basically ignore the ones that are small,
and you know, kind of use tricks to kind of, you know, improve the speed of the computation,
and this is what this does.
I'm not going to go into the details exactly what it does, because actually I don't know the details,
but it's basically an efficient approximation Softmax for a very very large number of categories.
So this is a special case of cross entropy when you only have two categories,
and in that case it kind of reduces to something simple.
So this does not include Softmax, this is just a cross entropy when you have two categories,
and as I said before, the cross entropy loss is the sum over categories of the probability,
I mean, sum over indices or sum over categories of the probability for the target probability for that category,
times the ratio between the log of the probability of produced by the system divided by the probability of the target category.
and if you work it out for two categories, necessarily one score is one minus the other one if you have two exclusive categories,
and it comes down to this. Okay?
Now, this supposes that X and Y are kind of probabilities that have to be strictly between 0 & 1,
I mean not strictly, but ...
well, kind of strictly because otherwise the logs gonna blow up.
Here is the KL divergence loss, I was tell you about earlier.
So here it's the ...
I mean it's return here in a funny form, but it's basically the ...,
Here again, it's sort of assumes ...
This is another one I was telling you about earlier actually this one is also a simplified one when you have a one-hot distribution for the target, so Y is a category.
But it has the disadvantage of not being merged with something like Softmax or log Softmax,
so it may reach, it may have kind of numerical issues.
Again it assumes X and Y are you know distributions.
This is barely used Poisson loss.
Okay, so this version of binary cross entropy here, takes scores that haven't gone through Sigmoid.
So this one does not assume that the X's are between 0 & 1,
it just takes, you know, values whatever they are.
And it passes them through a Sigmoid to make sure there are between 0 & 1 strictly.
Okay?
And so that is more likely to be a numerically stable.
It's a bit the same idea as kind of emerging log Softmax and negative log likelihood.
Very, yeah, same thing here. That's what I was talking.
Okay, margin losses. So this is sort of a important category of losses.
Those losses basically say if I have, in this case, two inputs,
the loss function here says I want one input to be larger than the other one by at least a margin.
Okay? So imagine the two inputs are scores for two categories.
You want the score for the correct category to be larger than the score for the incorrect category by at least some margin that you passed through the system.
And that's the formula you see down there, so it's basically a Hinge.
Okay? And it takes the difference between the two scores,
and so Y is a binary variable is +1 or -1,
and it controls whether you want X1 to be larger than X2,
or whether you want X2 to be larger than X1.
Okay?
We basically give it two scores,
and you tell it which one you want to be the larger score.
And then the cost function says, you know, if this one is larger than that one by at least a margin, then the cost is zero.
If it's smaller than the margin, or if it's in the other direction, and the cost increases linearly.
Okay? So that's called a Hinge loss.
Okay?
So that's very useful for a number of different things.
We've seen an example of this in .... so....
Yeah, for example, so this is sort of a margin ranking loss, so you have two values,
but there are sort of, this is a simplified version of it,
I mean there's a simpler version of it, which I don't have here for some reason.
We only have an X, okay?
So basically the loss is max of 0,
and -X times the margin,
and it just wants to make X smaller than the margin.
Right?
And so this is sort of a special case where you have a ranking between two scores of two categories.
So here is how you would use this for classification.
You would basically run your classifier; you would get scores.
Okay?
So before you do it in non-linearity weighted sums, and then you know the correct category,
so you say I want this correct category to have a high score,
and then what you do is you take another category that has the most offending score.
So either another category, so a category that is incorrect that has a higher score than the correct one,
or that has a lower score, but the lower score is too close.
Okay? So you take the category that who score is the closest to the correct one, or who score is higher than the correct one,
and you feed those two scores to the loss function like this,
so basically it's going to push up the score in the correct category, push down the score the incorrect category
until the difference is at least equal to the margin.
Okay?
That's you know a perfectly good way of training something in the context of an energy-based model,
for example, that's the sort of things you might want to do
you might want to say X1 or -X1 is the energy,
I mean X, you know, -X1 would be the energy of the correct answer,
and -X2 would be the energy of the incorrect answer.
like an a contrastive term an incorrect answer.
and you want to push down the energy of the correct answer, push up the energy of incorrect answer, so that the difference is at least sum margin.
Okay?
We can use this kind of loss for that.
The Triplet loss is gonna be refinement on this.
So this is used a lot for metric learning for the kind of Siamese nets that Ishan Misra was talking about last week.
And there the idea is, let's say I have a distance.
So let's say I have three samples;
I have one sample, and another sample is very similar to it.
I've run them to two convolutional nets, I get two vectors.
I compute the distance between those two vectors: d(ai, pi) for example.
okay?
I want to make this distance as small as possible, because that's the correct sample.
And then I take two samples that I know are semantically different.
Okay? The image of a cat and whatever, table.
and I want to make the vector as far away from each other.
So I compute the distance, and I want to make this distance large.
All right?
Now, I can insist that the first distance be 0,
and it can insist that the second distance be larger than the margin that would be kind of a margin loss type thing.
But what I can do is one of those triplet margin loss where I say
the only thing I care about is that the distance that I get for the good pair is smaller than the distance that I get for the bad pair.
I don't care if the distance is small,
I just wanted to be smaller than the distance for the bad pair.
Okay?
And that's what those ranking loss do.
A bunch of those were..
I mean one of the first I think that was proposed was by Jason Weston and Samy Bengio back when Jason Weston was to the Google.
And they used this to train kind of an image search system for Google,
so back then I'm not sure is true anymore,
but back then you would type a query on Google,
Google would encode that query into a vector,
then we compare this to a whole bunch of vectors describing images that I've been previously indexed,
and then would kind of retrieve the images whose vector were close to the one that you had,
and the way you train the networks that compute those vectors, in that case back then it was linear networks actually, is you train them with those triplet loss.
Okay, so you said good hits for my search should have a distance between the vectors that is smaller than any bad hit.
and I don't care if the distance is small, I just wanted to be smaller than for bad hits.
Any question?
That's kind of a graphical explanation of this where p is a positive sample,
so it's you know similar to "a".
So "a" is the sample you considered, p is kind of a positive sample, and n is a negative sample or contrastive sample.
You want to push n away and bring p closer,
and as soon as p is closer than n by some margin, you stop pushing and pulling.
Yeah, soft versions of this, and in fact, you can think of NCE, the kind of loss function that Ishan was talking about,
as kind of a soft version of that where you basically have a bunch of positives and bunch of negatives,
or you have one positive and bunch of negatives,
and you run them through a Softmax,
and you say I want this the, you know, e to the minus distance for the correct one to be smaller than, you know, e to the minus the other one,
so it kind of you pushes the positive closer to you and pushes the other ones further to you,
but now with some sort of Softmax-ie sort of exponential decay as opposed to sort of a hard margin
So in Pytorch you have things that allow you to have multi labels,
so this allows you to basically give multiple correct outputs.
This is a ranking loss but instead of insisting that there is only one correct category,
and you know, you want a high score for the correct category, and bad score for everything else.
Here you can have a number of categories for which you want high scores,
and then all the other ones will get pushed away.
All right, they'll get, the scores will be pushed down.
So here it's a hinge loss, but you do a sum of those this hinge loss over all categories.
and for each category, if the category is a desired one you push it up,
if it's a non-desired one you push it down, which is what this formula says.
Of course you have the soft version of this which I'm not going to go into the details of,
and the multi margin version of it.
So, this pushing and pulling for metric learning for embedding for Siamese nets that I was telling you about.
It's actually kind of all implemented if you want in one of those Hinge Embedding Loss.
So Hinge Embedding Loss is a loss for Siamese nets that kind of pushes things are semantically similar to you,
and push away things that are not. Okay?
So, the Y variable indicates whether the pair you are or whether the score you are giving to the system is one that should be pushed up, or one should be pushed down.
and it chooses the hinge loss that makes the score positive if Y is +1,
and it makes a score negative by some margin if Y is -1.
Very often when you are doing Siamese nets,
the way you compute the similarity between two vectors is not through Euclidean distance, but through cosine distance.
So the one minus the cosine of the angle between the two vectors,
this is basically a normalized Euclidean distance, if you want, you can think of it this way.
The advantage of this is that whenever you can push the distance,
whenever you have two vectors, and you want to make the distance as large as possible,
there's a very easy way for the system to get away with it by making the two vectors very large, very long,
you know, not pointing in the same direction and make them very very long,
so now the distance would be large.
But of course, that's not what you want.
You don't want the system to just make the vectors bigger;
you wanted to actually rotate the vector in the right direction.
So, you normalized the vectors, and then computed the normalized Euclidean distance, and that's basically what this does.
And what this does is that for positive cases, it tries to make the vectors as aligned with each other as possible,
and for negative pairs, it tries to make the cosine smaller than the particular margin.
The margin in that case should probably be something that kind of is close to zero.
So you want the cosine
in a high-dimensional space there's a lot of space near the equator of the sphere of the high-dimension sphere,
Okay, so all your points now are normalized on the sphere.
And what you want is samples that are semantically similar to you should be close to you,
but samples that are dissimilar should be orthogonal.
You don't want them to be opposed,
because there is only one point in the south pole,
whereas on the equator is a very very high large space, the entire sphere minus one dimension basically.
Okay?
So you can make the margin just, you know, so small positive value, and then you get the entire equator essentially of the sphere,
which contains the almost the entire volume of the sphere in high-dimension.
CTC Loss, this is a little more complicated,
because that's a loss that is basically uses structure prediction what's called structure prediction.
so this is... I sort of briefly talked about it very quickly a few weeks ago on something very similar to this.
So this is a loss is applicable when your output is a sequence of vectors of scores where the vectors correspond to scores of categories, okay?
And so you have ..., so your system computes a vector of such score.
So imagine, for example, speech recognition system.
Speech recognition system, every 10 milliseconds, gives you a vector of probabilities for what the sound being pronounced right now is,
and the number of categories usually is quite large on the order of a few thousand.
Okay? So give you basically a Softmax vector of a size, you know, typically 3000 let's say, one of those every 10 milliseconds.
All right?
And what you like, you know, you have a desired output, and the desired output is what word was being pronounced,
and a word that's being pronounced that corresponds to kind of a particular sequence of sounds if you want that you might you might know.
So what you need now is a cost that basically is low if that sequence looks like that sequence,
but what you might allow is for the input sequence to repeat some of the sounds, if you want.
Right?
So, for example, you know my cost to make the ..., the target might be the word seven let's say,
and it's pronounced really quickly, seven.
So you basically have, you know, a very small number of samples of each sound in the sequence.
But then perhaps the person who is pronouncing the word now that uses as a training sample pronounced it very slowly like seeevveeenn.
Right? So now the first "a" takes, you know, several frames of 10 milliseconds that should all be mapped to the the same instance of the "a" in the output.
And I do that picture before, but I gonna do it again.
Right? So you have ...
Let's see
You have a sequence of scores coming out of Softmaxes, let's say.
It's actually better if they are energies, but for CTC they need to be ...
and then you have the target sequence,
and think of this as some sort of matrix,
and each entry in that matrix basically measures the distance between the two vectors that are here.
Okay?
So one entry in the matrix indicates how this vector looks like that vector,
for example, with the cross entropy or something like that.
Okay?
Or squared error. It doesn't matter what the loss function is.
So now if this is the word seven pronounced slowly.
Okay?
and this has perhaps only one instance of each sound
You want all of those
you know, you would want all of those vectors corresponding to the "e" to be mapped to that "e" vector here.
Okay?
So you want to compute that cost of, you know,
confusing that those all of those, I mean, map matching those e's to that "e".
Now, of course here the system produce the correct answer,
so you don't have much of a problem,
but if the target is seven,
but the word that was pronounced here, or the output that was produced by the system does not correspond to seven,
that's when you run into trouble.
So here what you do is you find the best mapping from the input sequence to the output sequence.
Okay, so the "s" gets mapped to the "s", the "e" to the "e", the "v" to the "v",
the e's to the "e", and the "n" to the "n".
So you get this kind of path if you want that think of this as a path in the graph.
And the way determine this is basically by using a dynamic programming algorithm the shorted path algorithm that figures out how do I get from here to here
in the path that minimizes the sum of the distances between the all the vectors... all the distances between the vectors of, you know, all the points are going through.
Okay?
So there's a optimization respect to a latent variable if you want. Okay?
and CTC basically does that for you, right?
So you give it two sequences, and it computes the distance between them,
and you know, kind of the best kind of mapping between the two by allowing basically to map multiple input vectors to kind of a single one on the output,
it cannot expand it, it can only kind of reduce if you want.
And then that's done in a way that you can back propagate gradient to it.
We'll come back to this to more things like this at the end if you can.
oops
So this is what this the target is assumed to be many-to-one,
the alignment of the input to the target is assumed to be many-to-one,
which means the length of the target sequence such that it must be smaller than the length of the input.
That's for the reason I just explained.
Okay, so it's basically differentiable time-warping, you could think of it this way.
Or sort of a module that does dynamic time-warping or dynamic programming, and it's still differentiable.
The idea for this goes back in the early 90s in Lon Bottu PhD thesis, actually. That's very old.
Is there a good paper or resource to learn more about that dynamic programming algorithm there?
Actually, that's kind of what I'm gonna talk about next.
I may not have time to go through it, but I'll try to.
okay, but basically the last part of the energy based model tutorial,
Okay,
so the initial base model tutorial the 2006 paper that, we give you a reference a link to,
a tutorial on energy based models, the second part is all about this kind of stuff essentially.
Okay, so it's more energy based models, but now I'm gonna more of a supervised context if you want.
So
Preliminary, so before I get to this,
I want to come back to the sort of more general formulation of energy based models,
and the idea that ...
so if you want to kind of define energy based models in the proper way, these are the conditional versions,
you have a training set, a bunch of pairs (Xi, Yi), for i = 1 to P.
You have a loss functional. So, the loss functional L of (E, S).
So it takes the energy function computed by the system.
Okay?
and the training set, and it gives you a scalar value.
Now, you can think of this as a functional, so functional is a function of a function. Okay?
But in fact, because the energy function itself is parametrized by parameter W,
you can turn this loss functional into a loss function, which is not just a function of W another function of the energy function. Okay?
And of course the set of energy functions is called here is parametrized by the parameter W which is taken within the set.
So training consist in, of course minimizing the loss functional with respect to W and finding the W that minimizes it,
and so one question, you might ask yourself, you know,
I went to a whole bunch of objective function, loss functions here,
and the question is if you are in an energy based framework, what loss functions are good ones?
and what loss functions are bad ones?
how do you characterize a loss function that actually will do something useful for you?
Okay?
So here is a general formulation of the loss function, it's an average over training samples,
so here I'm kind of assuming that it's invariant under permutation of the samples.
So an average is as good as any other aggregation aggregating functions.
So it's the average over training samples of a per-sample loss function, capital L,
and it takes the desired answer Y which could be just a category, or it could be a whole image or whatever.
And it takes the energy function where the X variable Xi is equal to Xi, the i is training sample.
And the Y variable is undetermined. Okay?
So E(W,y,Xi) is basically the entire shape of the energy function for all values of Y, over values of Y, for a given X.
Okay? X equal to Xi.
And you can have a regularizer, if you want.
Okay? So here this is a loss functional again.
Again, of course we have to design this loss functional,
so that it makes the energy of correct answer small,
and the energy of incorrect answers large in some ways, right?
Okay. Now, we're going to go through a bunch of different types of loss functions.
So one thing we could do is say my loss function is just going to be the energy of the correct answer.
So I'm gonna place myself in the context of energy based model,
my system produces scores, I interpret those scores as energies,
so high is bad good is good, I mean low is good, as opposed to positive scores.
and what I'm just going to do is define my energy functional,
as a function of the energy function of the function of Y as simply the energy that my model gives to the correct answer.
Okay?
So basically I give it an X, and I give it the correct answer Y, and ask the system what energy do you give to that pair,
and then I try to make that energy as small as possible.
Okay?
So you have this landscape of energies here.
Now, I showed you this slide in the context of unsupervised self-supervised learning,
here I'm showing to you in the context of supervised learning.
So imagine that one of the variables is X, and the other variable is Y.
Okay?
And the blue beads are training samples, and you want to make the energy of the blue beads as small as possible.
So you're pulling down on the blue beads, but you're not doing anything else.
and so as a result depending on the architecture or your network,
if your network is not designed properly, or if it's designing in no particular way,
it could very well be that the energy function is going to become flat everywhere.
Okay? you're just trying to make the energy of the correct answer small,
and you not telling the system the energy of everything else should be higher,
and so the system might just collapse. All right?
So energy loss is not good in that sense,
but there are certain situations where it's applicable,
because if the shape of the energy function is such that, it cannot make the
it can only make the energy of a single answer small, the all the other ones being larger.
They don't need to have a contrastive term.
Okay? and we've seen this in the context of self-supervised learning.
People are completely lost about the loss functional.
Right, okay.
So this is a functional L, and it's a function of another function E, okay?
So it's called a functional, because it's a function of a function.
Right? It's not a function of a point, it's a function of a function.
Now, if that second function is parameterized by a parameter W,
then you can say that the loss function is actually a function of that parameter W, now, it becomes a regular function.
Okay, that's what I had in the ...
Can you can you write it down?
It's basically written here.
Okay, you can either write the functional as L(E,S), so that's a functional because it's a function of E which itself is a function.
Okay?
But E itself is a function of W,
and so, if I write the loss function directly as a function of W, now, it's just a regular function.
Okay?
Yeah, I mean I asked the question that was asked in the chat.
Yeah, I understand, I know.
Before that, you know for
Okay, we've seen the negative log likelihood loss before, I talked about this.
So this is a loss function that tries to make the energy of the correct answer ...
so look at the rectangle in red ...
tries to make the energy of the correct answer as low as possible.
And then you have the second term: 1/ log sum over all Y's of e to the -E(W,y,Xi)
and this one is trying to make the energy of all Y's for this given X as large as possible.
Okay? because the best way to make this term small is to make those energies large,
because they enter in there as a negative exponential.
Okay, so this has this kind of pushing down on the correct answer, pushing up on incorrect answer behavior.
And we've seen before. We just talked about margin loss and other types of losses.
Here is something that's called a perceptron loss,
because it's basically very similar to, I mean, it's exactly the same as the loss that was used for the perceptron over 60 years ago.
So this one says I want to make the energy of the correct answer small,
and the same time I want to make the energy of the the smallest energy for all answers as large as possible, okay?
So pick the Y that has the smallest energy in your system, make that as large as you can,
and the same time pick the correct energy, make that as small as you can.
Now, there is a point at which the answer with the correct energy is going to equal to the correct answer,
so that difference can never be negative. Okay?
Because the first term is necessarily one term in that minimum,
and so the difference is at best zero, and for every other cases is positive.
It's only zero when the system gives you the correct answer.
Okay?
But this objective function does not prevent the system from giving the very same energy to every answer.
So in that sense, it's a bad energy, it's a bad loss function.
It's a bad loss function because it says I want the energy of the correct answer to be small,
I want the energy of all the other answers to be large,
but I don't insist that there is any difference between them.
So the system can choose to make every answer the same energy.
And that's a collapse.
Okay, so perceptron loss is not good, it's actually only good for linear systems, but it's not good as a objective function for non-linear systems.
So here is a way to design an objective function that will always be good,
and you take the energy of the correct answer, and you take the energy of the most offending incorrect answer which means
the value of Y that is incorrect, but at the same time is the lowest energy of all the incorrect answers.
Okay?
And your system will work if that difference is negative.
In other words, if the energy of the correct answer is smaller than the energy of the most offending incorrect answer by at least some quantity, some margin.
Okay? So as long as your objective function will you design it ensures that
the energy of the correct answer is smaller than the energy of the most offending incorrect answer by at least some margin, nonzero margin,
then you'll fine, your loss function is good.
Okay, so things like hinge loss are good.
The hinge loss basically says, and we talked about this just before,
I want the energy of the correct answer to be smaller than the energy of the most offending incorrect answer,
which is denoted Yi-bar here, by at least m.
Okay? This is what this loss function does. It's a hinge loss,
and it wants to push down the energy of this guy below the energy of that guy by at least this margin.
So this has a margin m,
and this will, you know, if you train a system with this loss, it will and it can run the task.
you will run the task, and probably produce the good answers.
The hinge loss, the soft hinge loss, which is in the context of energy based models is expressed this way,
basically instead of feeding the difference between the energies of the correct answer and the most offending incorrect one in to a hinge,
it feeds it to a soft hinge.
Okay, which we talked about 30 minutes ago
And there, this was also has a margin, the margin of
How to pick m? the question would be how to pick m?
It's arbitrary. You can set m to 1, you can set m to 0.1.
I mean, it's kind of arbitrary because it will just determine the size of the weights of your last layer.
That's all it does. Okay?
So it's basically up to you.
Yeah, so the soft hinge loss has an infinite margin.
it wants the difference between those two energies to be infinite,
but the slope decreases exponentially,
so it's never going to get there because, you know, the gradients get very small as the difference increases.
Here's another example of a margin loss, the square loss, the square-square loss. Okay?
So this is a loss that tries to make the energy of the correct answer squared as small as possible,
and then it has a square hinge to push away to push up the energy of the most offending incorrect answers.
Okay, and again that works, and this is very similar to the kind of loss that people use in Siamese nets and stuff like that you've heard about.
There's a whole menagerie of such losses, which I'm not going to go through.
There's actually a whole table here, which is also in this paper the tutorial energy based models,
and what's indicated on the right side is whether they have a margin or not.
So the energy loss does not have a margin, it doesn't push up anything,
so no margin, it doesn't work always,
you have to design the machine, so that this loss may work for that system.
The perceptron loss does not work in general,
it only works if you have a linear parameterization of your energy as a function of the parameters,
but that's a special case, and that's the case for the perceptron,
and then some of them have a finite margin like the hinge loss,
and some of them have an infinite margin like the log, the soft hinge, if you want.
Whole bunch of those losses some of those were used were invented in the context of discriminative learning for speech recognition systems,
but not ... they were invented before people in machine learning actually got interested in this.
The question would be like how you find the Y-bar?
So if you have like a discrete code, we can find simply like, you know, the minimum value.
But otherwise, are we running gradient descent?
Right, so if Y is continuous,
then there is no kind of clear definition for what is the most offending incorrect answer, okay?
You will have to define some sort of distance around the correct answer, above which you consider an answer to be incorrect.
Okay? So for example you are in a continuous energy landscape, there is one training sample here.
You want to make that the energy of that training sample small easy enough,
compute the energy through your neural net, push it down, back propagate, update the weight.
So that the energy goes down, easy enough.
Now, the incorrect answer if you take an answer that just kind of outside of that,
and you push up,
you know, your energy surface might be a little stiff because it's computed by a parameterized neural net, so that may not be possible.
So you probably want to have a incorrect answer that's, you know, quite a bit outside that you're gonna, you know, push up.
And so that's how you define, you know, the whole question is how you define the contrastive sample that you gonna push up.
And the a lot of those objective functions here, those loss functions use a single, you know, Y-bar, negative sample.
But there is no single correct way of picking this Y-bar,
you can imagine, you know, particularly in the kind of, in the sort of continuous case, or
in the case where Y is either very very large or continuous and high-dimensional.
There's no simple way to pick Y-bar.
You know a lot of discussions we've had about contrastive methods that Ishan talked about for Siamese nets and that we talked about before,
where basically, how do you pick a Y-bar in the self-supervised case, in the self-supervised you don't have X.
Right?
And, you know, there is many ways you can pick it up,
it's only obvious how to pick it up in kind of small cases.
I just want to point out the formula here at the bottom,
so this is a kind of you can think of this as sort of, a general form of, sort of hinge type, contrastive losses where
you have an H function here, think of it as a hinge of some type.
Okay?
and instead of that hinge, you have the energy of the correct answer,
so that's the energy of (W,Yi,Xi),
so this is your training sample, that's the energy of the system gives to the training sample.
The second term is the energy of some/sum other answer, y, okay?
for the same X training sample,
and then there is a margin, but that margin C is actually a function of Yi and y,
and you might imagine the margin is actually also a function of X and Xi.
So basically you determine a margin as a function of the distance between the Y's.
Okay?
and you feed that to let's say a hinge.
Now, the thing is
this loss function is summed over all Y's,
here is a discrete song, because Y is discrete, but you could imagine an integral.
Okay?
So this kind of loss says, you know, I have an energy for my correct answer,
I have energies for every other answer in my space,
and I want to push up the energy of all other answers,
but the amount by which I want to make them higher the margin depends on the distance between Y and Y-bar,
or in this case between Yi which is this, and y which is the otherwise.
Okay, so you could imagine that this margin will come, you know, will come smaller and smaller as the two y is gonna get closer to each other,
in this case, you don't push up too much for things are too close than you push up in proportion to the distance of the Y,
you know, whatever distance you think is appropriate.
This is of course a more difficult loss function to optimize.
I'm outta time, so I might talk about the structure prediction issue that I said I was going to talk about at the later time.
Any more question?
The contrastive method for the self-supervised learning papers,
they are usually ??? take the random images as the negative examples.
Do you have any idea have been used these functions anyone's tried experimented with these?
Either use what kind of function?
These loss functions that you explain to us now.
So most of them use the basically the negative log likelihood loss here, which in this panel is called NLL/MMI.
Okay, so NCE that you heard about from Ishan, that's what they used, right?
They're trying to make the distance between the samples as small as possible,
and then the contrastive term is, you know, is basically your log softmax of the distances.
So when you compute the log softmax, you think of a distance as an energy,
and then you compute the log softmax of those energies,
you get this formula here in the second last line called NLL/MMI.
MMI means maximum, ???? approximated by taking random images?
The random what?
Making random images as negative example, so that will use for approximate the integral?
Well, so basically you can't compute this integral over all Y, so
or this a sum if Y is discrete,
and so you basically approximate the sum by, you know, a few terms that you pick randomly.
Right?
Yeah. That's called Monte Carlo.
I mean basically if you want to do this properly, you have to pick those samples according to the rule of Monte Carlo sampling,
but it doesn't matter. I mean that's why hard-negative mining is hard.
Okay, that's why what makes the difference between MoCo, PIRL, SimCLR, etc is how you pick those negative samples.
That's why I said there is no kind of in cases where Y space is high-dimensional, there is no, you know, predefined way of picking negative samples essentially.
It's only in classification that this easy.
Have other people experiment about other losses?
Yeah, I mean there are a lot of people are using the square-square or the sort of hinge, you know, with the difference of energies,
so some of the systems are being used by at least at some point,
the system that deep face which is the face recognition system that used by Facebook to tag people.
It used the convolutional net trained in supervised mode with a certain number of categories basically images from, I don't know, million people or something,
but then there is a fine-tuning phase that use metric learning basically Siamese nets
where you show two photos of the same person, and you say those are the same person,
and then two photos of different people, and you push them apart,
and that used, they tried different objective functions,
but I think they were using the square-square loss at some point, or maybe the squared exponential ,
and, now, entirely sure what they're using now, but, you know, it's one of those.
Professor, what topics will you covered in the next lecture?
Okay, so we're gonna have two guest lectures,
so next is Mike Lewis, Mike Lewis is a research scientist at Facebook AI research in Seattle,
and he is a specialist of natural language processing and translation,
so it's gonna, you know, tell you all the interesting tidbits about sequence to sequence, about transformers, about NLP, and about translation.
Okay?
And you know, he knows a lot, you know, much better the details about this than I do, so he's the right person to talk about this.
We're gonna have another guest lecture is going to be Xavier Bresson.
He is, you know, one of the world specialist of graph neural nets.
So this is the whole idea of, you know, how do you apply neural nets,
you know, you can think of an image as a function on a regular grid, okay?
every pixel is a location on a regular grid, you can think of an image as a function on that grid, okay?
So grid is a graph of a particular type, and the image is just a function on the graph.
You can think of, I don't know, a video as, you know, a regular 3D-grid where you have space and time,
and you know, most natural signals you can think of them as functions on kind of regular graphs, okay?
What about the case where the function you're interested in is not on the euclidean graph if you want?
So let's imagine, for example, you take a photo with a panoramic camera, okay? 360 camera, right?
So it's a camera that basically takes a spherical image, okay?
So now your pixels live on the sphere, how do you compute the convolution on the sphere?
Okay?
So you want to run your convolutional net on this image that now lives on the sphere,
You can't use the standard ways of computing convolutions.
So you have to figure out how to compute convolutions on the sphere.
Right?
So that's an example.
Now, here's something a little more complicated, imagine now that you have a 3D-scanner,
and you're capturing, I don't know, a dancer, you know, someone kind of in front of a 3D-scanner.
and that person has a particular pose, let's say like this. Okay?
And then you take another 3D-picture, 3D-data from another person.
And that other person is, you know, in another pose.
That person has a different body shape, she's in a different body pose.
And now what you want is you want to be able to map one on to the other,
you want to be able to say like, you know, what is the hand in the first person? where is the hand in the second person?
so what you have to do now is basically have a neural net that takes into account a 3D-mesh that represents the geometry of a hand,
and train it to tell you it's a hand.
So that when you apply it to the hand, it tells you it's a hand,
when you apply to the other parts of the body, it tells you it's something else,
but the data you have is not an image, it's a 3D-mesh.
Okay?
The mesh may have different resolutions, the triangles make here occur at different places,
so how you define your convolutions on the domain like this that is independent of the resolution of the mesh,
and only kind of depends on the shape,
so that you can classify a hand regardless of the orientation, the size, the conformation,
and the body shape of the person, you know, things like that, right?
So, here's another example, that's perhaps more interesting.
You want to do, you want to train something like a Siamese net,
but you want to train this Siamese net to tell you
whether one molecule is going to stick to another molecule, right?
So you give two molecules to your neural net, and the neural net produces two vectors,
if those two molecules stick together, it gives you two vectors whose distance is small.
Okay?
And if they don't stick together, then the distance is large.
Okay, so you can think of the distance as kind of the negative free energy of the binding,
the binding energy of the two, you know, the two molecules.
Right?
Or the, you know, the the free energy, you know, minus a constant if you want.
So ...
So you would train this as a Siamese net,
but then the problem is how you represent a molecule to a network knowing that it's the same network you're going to apply to this molecule on that molecule,
and the two molecules don't have the same shape, they don't have the same length,
they don't have the same number of atoms, they don't have the same ...
Like how do you represent a molecule?
The best way to represent a molecule is as a graph.
It's basically a graph whose structure changes with the molecule,
and this graph is annotated by the identity of the atoms at each site
maybe by the location in 3D-space for their relative location,
maybe by the angle of the bonds between two successive atoms,
or the binding energy of that particular bond or things like this.
So ...
so the best way to represent a molecule is by representing as a graph basically,
and there's another example, perhaps more relevant to something like Facebook.
Let's say ...
Let's say I want to kind of infer, or let's say Amazon or something.
I want to infer what type of ...
Let's say I'm Amazon, right?
and I have a customer, and that customer has bought a whole bunch of different things,
and that customer has commented of whole bunch of different things.
I could think of kind of encoding this as a vector, but it would be a vector of variable size,
because you know people buy different numbers of things and stuff like that,
so we need to, so find a way to aggregate that data,
so that everybody can be represented by the same fixed size vector,
but what if instead, I represent the person, and all the things that that person has bought, and all the, you know, reviews that person are made, and etc as a graph essentially.
and then I represent what I feed to the neural net is the graph with values on the nodes and perhaps the arcs.
if I have a way of representing a graph, so that it can connect a neural net independently of the shape of the graph,
then I can do this kind of application.
And so this is what graph neural nets are about. It's a very very hot topic at the moment.
It's extremely promising for a lot of applications particularly in biomedicine,
you know, in chemistry, in material science, but also in social science for the social network analysis,
and you know, all kinds of applications, computer graphics, you know, all kind of the stuff.
So it's really cool.
Xavier is really one of the experts on this topic, so I'm really happy that he accepted to give us a talk.
So it's not gonna be easy for him because he is in Singapore.
So he's gonna be fine the morning for him.
That's right.
Well, I'm giving a lecture in a couple days in Hong Kong, so same thing for me.
I see. So, actually, he's from Nanyang Technological University
NTU, right?
NTU, Yeah.
Yeah. I was confused, correct.
All right? so that was it.
Sorry, there is one more questions.
Yeah, that was really interesting professor.
I have one more question. I was reading this term called normalizing flows.
Yeah
and I don't understand what they are?
Could you just give some intuition into why people are excited about it?
Right.
So normalizing flows
So it's not a technic that have a lot of experience with, but, you know, I've read the papers.
it's
so it's proposed by Danilo Rezende and Shakir Mohamed at DeepMind
a while ago, and a while back, maybe five years ago or so.
and it's basically a sort of a density estimation method, so it's a little bit like Gans.
It has a bit of the same spirit as Gans,
and it gets inspiration from ICA (independent component analysis).
Although it's not kind of explicit in the original paper, but here's the basic idea.
Basic idea is you want to train a neural net to transform a known distribution from which you can sample, into a distribution that happens to be the distribution of your data.
Okay?
So let's imagine that you have a latent variable z that you sample from a gaussian distribution,
and you run it through a function or uniform distribution over a domain, Okay?
You run it through a function implemented by neural net,
and you want to train this neural net that, so that the distribution you get at the output is the one you want that corresponds to your data.
Okay?
and
So the
Let me give you a very simple example.
So let's say have a variable z, and have observed variable y,
and I sample my variable z with the uniform distribution, okay? between say 0 and 1.
Okay?
and what I want on the output is, I don't know, say gaussian.
It's kind of stupid to want to gaussian, but it's say I want the gaussian, because I could sample from a gaussian easily.
So what I need to do is kind of transform this uniform distribution into a gaussian by a mapping
and the mapping is going to be a function like ...
It's gonna be if function ...
Okay? zero is here.
Kind of like this if you want.
Okay
And this is the inverse of the integral of the gaussian distribution.
Okay?
So if I take the derivative of this function, okay.
So, now, let me kind of draw this.
It's a little difficult to see, but if I map.
Okay, the derivative of this function here will indicate how much I stretch a little piece here into a piece here, right?
So the larger the derivative, the more I stretch, right?
If the slope here is 1, then this piece of the distribution here is not going to stretch,
it's going to be kind of passed unchanged, okay?
And the larger the slope, the more stretch the distribution,
I stretch a little piece here,
and therefore, I kind of distribute all the samples that fall into this, you know, location here, I stretched them over a large region.
Right?
And so what I need to do is design this function in such a way that stretches my input distribution,
so that, that distribution get transformed into the output distribution I want.
All right?
So there is a formula that says
so in multi-dimension is a little more complicated than this, but it says that the distribution you're going to get on y
is going to be equal to the distribution that you started with in z
multiplied by the inverse of the determinant of the Jacobian of this f function, so this is f.
minus 1
So it's actually the original formula is this one,
but those two things are equal.
Okay?
So if you take, so this is for a multi-dimensional vector function, right?
So it has a Jacobian to map z to y,
and so if you take the determinant of the inverse Jacobian of that function,
which is a scalar value indicates by how much the distribution get stretched, or compressed in that case at q.
So in that case here it's the compression ratio, it's the inverse of the derivative, so it's the compression.
Right? And so the more you compress here, the more the probability will be high,
more p(y) will be large, the density p(y) for this y will be large for a given q.
So this is for y equals f(z).
Okay?
So the big question of normalizing flow methods is how you do this, right?
given a number of samples of p(y), and given that you sample your distribution q, you have your distribution q you sample from it.
You know, how do you kind of minimize an objective function that
knowing that you know,
the p you get at the output is equal to the q you put at the input multiplied by this inverse determinant of the Jacobian of the f function.
What you have to find is the f function, so basically you have to differentiate.
So basically it compute the distance between those, you know, divergence, KL divergence for example, between p(y) and the thing on the right side of the equal sign.
And you have to differentiate this with respect to the parameters of f.
So you have to basically propagate through the inverse gradient of the Jacobian of f, right?
It's not easy.
Very often what people do is that they write f as a succession a very simple f's that only modify the distribution just a little bit,
So f very often is, you know, something like the identity plus some deviation, a bit like ResNet if you want,
and then you stack lots and lots of layers of that, and the problem becomes simpler,
because when those functions do a little bit of modification,
then the a lot of those kind of issues can become simple the determinant here kind of simplifies.
Okay, that's a very sort of abstractable description of normalizing flow.
There is interesting papers about this in recent years on, even recent months, on sort of using this for like particle physics and stuff like that.
Kyle Cranmer at NYU is actually a kind of a specialist of that.
Thank you so much professor.
All right, any other question?
Okay, that was it.
Great, thank you very much everyone.
Yeah, see you tomorrow guys.
All right.
Bye Bye.
Take care.